<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Clerico-classicum, or, The clergi-allarum to a third war. Being an answer to a pamphlet, intituled, A serious and faithfull representation of the judgements of ministers of the Gospel within the province of London, contained in a letter from them to the Generall and his Councell of Warre. Delivered to his Excellency by some of the subscribers, Jan. 18. 1648. Which may likewise serve for a brief answer to their late vindication, relating to their former actings, touching the capitall punishment of the person of the King. / By John Price, citizen of London.</title>
            <author>Price, John, Citizen of London.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3340</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E544_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204338</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863898</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863898</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116114</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90963)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116114)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 84:E544[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Clerico-classicum, or, The clergi-allarum to a third war. Being an answer to a pamphlet, intituled, A serious and faithfull representation of the judgements of ministers of the Gospel within the province of London, contained in a letter from them to the Generall and his Councell of Warre. Delivered to his Excellency by some of the subscribers, Jan. 18. 1648. Which may likewise serve for a brief answer to their late vindication, relating to their former actings, touching the capitall punishment of the person of the King. / By John Price, citizen of London.</title>
                  <author>Price, John, Citizen of London.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 57, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.S. for H. Cripps, in Popes-head Allie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648 [i.e. 1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb. 19".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Serious and faithfull representation of the judgments of ministers of the Gospel within the province of London.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116114:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116114:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CLERICO-CLASSICUM,
OR,
The Clergi-allarum to a third war.</p>
            <p>Being an Anſwer to a Pamphlet,
INTITULED,
A Serious and Faithfull repreſentation of the
judgements of Miniſters of the Goſpel with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
the Province of <hi>London,</hi> contained in a Letter
from them to the Generall and his Councell of
Warre.</p>
            <p>Delivered to his Excellency by ſome of the Subſcribers,
Jan. 18. 1648.</p>
            <p>Which may likewiſe ſerve for a brief anſwer to their
late Vindication, relating to their former actings, touching
the Capitall puniſhment of the Perſon of the King.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Price,</hi> Citizen of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>MALACHI, 2. 7, 8, 9.</bibl>
            <q>
               <p>For the Prieſts lips ſhould keepe knowledge, and they ſhould ſeeke the
Law at his mouth: for he is the Meſſenger of the Lord of Hoſts.</p>
               <p>But ye are departed out of the way: ye have cauſed many to ſtumble at
the law: ye have corrupted the Covenant of <hi>Levi</hi> ſaith the Lord of hoſts.</p>
               <p>Therefore have I alſo made you contemptible, and baſe before all the
people, according as yee have not kept my wayes, but have been partiall
in the Law.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authority.</p>
            <q>Men who lye under the guilt of much innocent blood, are not
meet perſons to be at peace with, till all the guilt of blood be
expiated and avenged, either by the Sword of the Law, or Law
of the Sword, elſe a peace can neither be ſafe nor juſt:</q>
            <bibl>
               <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher
Love,</hi> page 37. of his <hi>Englands Diſtemper.</hi>
            </bibl>
            <p>LONDON,
Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>H. Cripps,</hi> in Popes-head Allie, 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:116114:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116114:2"/>
            <head>To His Excellency <hi>Thomas,</hi> Lord
<hi>Fairfax,</hi> and his Councell of Warre.
And the Honourable the Lord Preſident and high Court
of Juſtice.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Excellency and Honours.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the olde enmity between Sathan &amp; Saints
hath been alwayes improved by power and policie,
yet the Serpents ſeede appearing in or opes, and
the Serpents head applying his traps, have beene
hitherto cruſh't by the foo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of truth, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
thereof; It is hard to ſay whether <hi>Iſraels</hi> Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annt,
and <hi>Iſraels</hi> Aſſaultant, have more hotly diſputed in combates
or counſels: but frequent experiences, and faithfull promiſes doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly
certifie, that neither weapon nor wiſdome ſhall ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
God; yet <hi>Balack</hi> and <hi>Balaain,</hi> the Prince and the Prieſt
(as of old, ſo now) from <hi>Piſga</hi> to <hi>Peor</hi> (or Pulpit to Pulpit) pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume
to bleſſe the Lord by curſing his Armies, as if God would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change
the blood of his people for that of Buls and Goates,; for their
talke of Reformation, give them (the longing of their ſoules) the
Armies deſtruction:<note place="margin">Numb. 25. 24.</note> Nevertheleſſe <hi>the people ſhall riſe up as a
great Lion, and lift up himſelfe as a young Lion; hee ſhall
not lye down till he eate of the prey; and drink the blood of
the ſlain.</hi> It is not one of the leaſt advantages of Iſraels adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,
that they know their colours can ſpeake their language, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
their word; by meanes whereof their deceitfull ſpies come
to their counſels, finde out their purpoſes; nay ſometimes get under
pay, procure preferment, and draw out parties, as <hi>Abſolom</hi> did,
400. men, that in the ſimplicity of their hearts, knowing nothing,
did follow their Leader) to their own ruine; the inconſiderate ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription
of ſo many judicious, grave, and learned men to that abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive.
Letter ſent in private to your Excellency and generall Councell
out of their Chriſtian amity, and publiſhed in print to procure your
infamy, ſcandalouſly aſperſing the High Court of Juſtice, delivered
<hi>Jan.</hi> 18. 1648. doth abundantly argue the yet living efficacie of
<pb facs="tcp:116114:3"/>
that Serpents ſubtlety, which (with Gods words in the lip)
cheated our firſt Parents into moſt deceitfull actions. Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
ſome <hi>Judas</hi> or Jeſuite under the ſhape of a Brother, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
their Function, hath got this ſubſcription, ſince the publiſhing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
(as a due puniſhment (they have run the gauntlet, each tongue &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
hath a laſh at their nakedneſſe. For although it be your glory to paſſe
by your injuries, yet it is our duty to vindicate your innocencie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey
charge you with perjurie for keeping your Covenant, in bringing Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents
to condign puniſhmeut; they charge you with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>,
for a judiciall execution of the grand murtherer of this latter age;
they charge you with break<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the Parliament, for not permitting
them to enſlave &amp; ruine (their Lord) the Kingdome. Honour'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>,
ſuffer not their chantings to obſtruct your proceedings; they pretend a
meſſage from <hi>your</hi> Lord and theirs; containing an inhibition of his
expreſſe command<note n="a" place="margin">Numb. 35. 16, 17.</note>, and a plain contradiction to their fello. Miniſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
opinion<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn Knox</hi> his hiſtory of the reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of religion in the Realme of Scotland, l. 4. p. 397. wher he aſſerteth it to be the judgement of <hi>Calvin,</hi> and of the moſt god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and moſt learned Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines that ce in Europe, that the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and upon their fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall default, the people may &amp; ought to execute their Princes for murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their liege Subjects.</note>. I have not the leaſt enmity againſt lawfull Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
nor the ſmalleſt reluctance againſt the publique Miniſtery, the one
and the other being Gods Ordinances for our preſent &amp; eternal good:
but whom Magiſtrates ſhall enſlave, and Miniſters deceive, and
both officiate for their private intereſt, they are moſt noxius to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
benefit: when that <hi>Caleb</hi> leades Iſrael that <hi>will follow the
Lord fully,</hi> and that man is found out that <hi>will ſeek judgement &amp;
execute the truth.</hi> Wee may hopefully expect our duction by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
into the land of Promiſe, though through ſeverall combates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
ſons of Anacke, and our happineſſe by the other through a pacificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of an angry GOD, who will ſpare the NATION by juſt
execution: The preſence of GOD, and the prayers of his people
(whoſe guard you are in thoſe troubleſome times) ſhall ever attend
your juſt attempts: And although your zealous Enemies, under the
ſpecious pretences of a pious Reformation, and deepe devotion, doe
faſt for ſtrife and debate, and to ſtrike with the fiſt of wickedneſſe; yet
while you looſe the bonds of wickedneſſe, &amp; und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the heavy burt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ens,
free the oppreſſed, and breake every yoke; your light ſhall breake forth
as the morning, and your health ſhall ſpring forth ſpeedily; your
righteouſneſſe ſhall goe before you, and the glory of the Lord ſhall be
your rearward<note n="c" place="margin">Iſa. 58. 8.</note>: ſo prayeth, and ſo believeth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your daily remembrancer at the throne of grace, JOHN PRICE.</signed>
               <date>February 18. 1648.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116114:3"/>
            <head>Clerico-Clasſicum,
OR
THE CLERGY-ALARUM
TO A
THIRD WARRE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat <hi>the Prieſts lips ſhould preſerve know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 2. 7, 8.</note>
whereby men may be incourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to <hi>ſeeke the Law at their monthes,</hi> in
the Scriptures aſſertion, that they
have often <hi>departed out of the way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zachar. 13. 3. Jer. 23. 21.</note>
               <hi>and cauſed many to ſtumble,</hi> is moſt
mens obſervation, and the old Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
of a preſumptuous arrogation
to themſelves <hi>the name of the Lord,</hi> and of his miſſion (when
<hi>he ſent them not</hi>) to charme the people into a credulo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of their deceitfull ſayings, is ſtill in uſe, a proofe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
is newly exhibited in a late Pamphlet; whoſe Frourice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece
flouriſheth with the ſpecious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wordxs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of deep devotion; cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
it, <hi>A SERIOVS AND FAITHF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LL RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PRESENTATION
OF THE J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DGEMENTS
OF MINISTERS OF THE GOSPELL WITH
IN THE PROVINCE OF LONDON, CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAINED
IN A LETTER FROM THEM TO
THE GENERALL AND HIS CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCELL
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116114:4"/>
OF WARRE, DELIVERED TO HIS EXCEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LENCY
BY SOME OF THE S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BSCRIBERS
JAN:</hi> 18. 1648. wherein we obſerve:</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Letter writers, ſet forth, firſt by their function,
<hi>Miniſters of the Goſpell:</hi> ſecondly, the place of their reſidence
and relation, <hi>WITHIN THE PROVINCE OF
LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the perſons to whom it wan written, <hi>THE
GENERALL AND HIS CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCELL OF
WARRE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, the nature and ſubject matter of this Letter,</hi> viz.
ASERIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S AND FAITHF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LL REPRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SENTATION
OF THEIR J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DGEMENTS, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Jer. 23. 21.</note> the Letter-writers are (as they ſay) <hi>Miniſters of
the Goſpell,</hi> ſo the falſe Prophets of old, pretended to be the
Prophets of the Lord; ſo the Pope, Chriſts grand Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour
and Vicar upon earth, ſo the Popiſh Prieſts and Jeſuits,
the Miniſters of Chriſt; ſo the Prelates, and Prelaticall Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
Vicars, and Curats, the Miniſters of the Goſpell; ſo
many others as faithfull, ſerious, judicious, learned, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
as theſe that are of quite contrary judgement to them, and
the contents of this Letter, doe ſtile themſelves the Miniſters
of Chriſt, meſſengers of the Goſpell, &amp;c. Which of theſe
ſhall the people beleeve? Surely who ever among them can
vindicate their Divine origination, theſe men have adminiſtred
cauſe ſufficient to queſtion their abilities hereunto, eſpecially
concerning the preſent Meſſage, which in the name of the Lord
they here tender unto the Generall and the Councell of Warre
as from the Lord, wherein they doe very authoritatively, as
from Chriſt, charge them for acting things <hi>clearely againſt the
direct rule of the Word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 3.</note> though they poynt not to the Text,
and ſome of them have promoted, incouraged, and abetted,
the very ſelfe ſame actions done at another time by other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
(as we ſhall ſpeake too anon) which here they have ſo
anathamatized and branded as an accurſed thing, as if theſe
men had the liberty and power (and that from Jeſus Chriſt)
of making the ſame actions, with all their circumſtances
(their owne intereſt excepted) one while good, honourable,
<pb facs="tcp:116114:4"/>
and commendable, and another while wicked, vile, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable;
a prerogative which the Almighty himſelfe never
yet claimed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for the place of their reſidence and relation,
<hi>THE PROVINCE OF LONDON<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> poore London,
<hi>Thy Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phets make thee to erre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Micha 3. 5.</note> 
               <hi>that bite with their teeth, and
hee that putteth not into their mouths, they even prepare Warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
him;</hi> how art thou precipitated and hurryed by thy
Teachers into oblique, croſſe, and contrary actions; one while
ſome of them pretend to a Viſion <hi>from the Lord,</hi> commanding
thee to doe <hi>this thing;</hi> when (at the ſame time) other<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of thy
See<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have the ſame pretence to a contrary Viſion, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
thee ſtill <hi>in the name of the Lord,</hi> and <hi>in the authority of
Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to the moſt contrary action; ſome injoyning
thee, <hi>a from the Lord,</hi> to goe no to <hi>Ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oth Giliad</hi> and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
others <hi>in the ſame name,</hi> conjuring thee not to goe up up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
pains of periſhing; one while thou muſt take up Annes,
by the inſtigation of thy Miniſters, requiring and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
thee <hi>in the name of the Lord,</hi> with fire and Sword to aſſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
and maintaine <hi>the cauſe of God, the truth of Jeſus Chriſt, de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie
of his worſhip: viz.</hi> The Prelaticall faction, or the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
intereſt of (<hi>the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt</hi>) the Clergy
thereof; another while thou muſt arme thy ſelfe, from the
ſame inſtigations, <hi>in the name of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to ſacrifice thy
Gold and thy Silver, thy Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye and thy Plate, thy Horſes
and thy ſervants, thy very life and being, upon the happy
promotion of the houſe of God, the government of Chriſt;
a bleſſed Reformation! the ſuppreſſion of error, hereſie, and
blaſphemy (otherwiſe more cruely called, the ſervice and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts,
honour and preferments, of (the Miniſters of Jeſus
Chriſt) the Presbyterian Clergie, and the cauſe thereof;
how muſt thou put on thy Armour and put it off againe, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance
and retreat, doe and undoe, according to the crooked
motions of thy uncertaine Teachers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ormenting thy minde,
vexing thy thoughts, and harracing thy perſon into contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
actions by their contrary orders, by meanes whereof, the
ancient love, union, and goodneſſe of thine Inhabitants, is
turned into hatted, diviſion, and bitterneſſe, each againſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116114:5"/>
cauſing thy foundation to ſhake, and thy pillars to
tremble, which is all the benefit thou haſt received by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change
of thy late Dioceſſe for <hi>THE PROVINCE OF LON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing conſiderable, is the perſons to whom this
devout letter was written and delivered, <hi>viz. THE GENE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RALL
AND HIS COVNCELL OF WARRE,</hi>
though chiefely intended for the mutions, malignant, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed,
and diſtemper'd party of the common people; that
theſe letters (by the midwifery of <hi>James Cranford,</hi> that bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull
and liberall Imprimatur-donor to any lying, ſcurrious,
and ſcandalous Pamphlet againſt the Parliament and Army)
might ſtirre them up (if poſſible) to any deſperats, bloody,
and dangerous attempt, to interrupt the preſent current of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
to hunt after, and to procure at laſt, that ſavory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
which the ſoules of theſe zealous Clergy-men ſo greatly long
for, <hi>viz.</hi> to be liſted up into the chaire of impulſory authority
and government, though it be by the ruines of their native
Countrey, ſo that that which <hi>Gregory</hi> writ to <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>riti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
the ambition of the Preliticall Patriarcks of <hi>Conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inople,</hi>
may be as truly ſaid of our preſent Clergy-men; <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re
compellor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. Epiſt. 323.</note> 
               <hi>ac dicere ô tempora <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mores <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cuncta in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
partibus, barbarorum juri ſunt tradita, deſtructae urbes everſo caſtra
depopulatae provinciae,</hi> &amp;c. That is, <hi>I am compelled to cry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Oh
times, Oh manners; behold in all the par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Europe all things cry
under the reverence of barbarous people, Townes are deſtroyed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iles
overthrowne, Provinces are ſpoyled, no labourer inhabiteth
the Land; notwithſtanding the Prieſts, who ſhould lye in uſhes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the ground weeping, they are ſeeking unto themſelves names of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi>
&amp;c. Nay have not we cauſe to ſay that the like things have
befallen us by the only meanes and procurement of the men of
this function; for was not the rice of the late ſadde and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
Warres, the pride and arrogancy of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe that ſtiled
themſelves <hi>the Miniſters of the Goſpell, the Embaſſadors of Chriſt,
viz.</hi> the proud Prelates: And was not the late ſecond Warre,
and the flames thereof inkindled and blown up by the Pulpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incondiaries,
the like Miniſters of the Goſpel, Embaſſadors
of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> The ambitious Presbyters, who are now
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116114:5"/>
againe by their fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y tongues and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urious pens, ſcattering their
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Pamphlets among the people, and hiſſing them on to
a third Warre, reſolving (as it appeare) to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the Kingdome
in aſhes, but they will have their wiſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>A third and laſt thing conſiderable in the Title of this letter,
is the nature and ſubject-matter thereof, <hi>viz. A SERIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S
AND FAITHF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LL REPRESENTATION OF
THEIR J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DGEMENTS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That you are <hi>ſerious and faithfull</hi> in the proſecution of your
<hi>judgemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> general, touching your own intereſt, power, and
preferment, we have reaſon enough to believe: but how ſhall
wee know when you are <hi>ſerious and faithfull</hi> in the <hi>REPRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SENTATION</hi>
of your <hi>judgement</hi> in any particular; for we
ſhall anon minde you of a <hi>repreſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation</hi> of your <hi>judgements,</hi> and
that by your ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lves, as far differing from this, as light i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from
darkneſſe, and yea from nay: and we had as much and more
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſon to believe your <hi>ſeriouſneſſe</hi> and <hi>faithfulneſſe</hi> in that <hi>repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation</hi>
of your <hi>judgements,</hi> then in this; the right eye whereof
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> darkened, and the right hand ſo withered, that there is
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the leaſt glimmering or motion of light, or arguments
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or your <hi>judgement repreſented</hi> in all your letter: and did not a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſumptuous opinion ſwell in your mindes, that your very
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mes, titles, and preſumed vocation, <hi>viz.</hi> (Miniſters of the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſpell, Embaſſadours of Jeſus Chriſt) would challenge a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uddaine entertainement of what ever you <hi>repreſent,</hi> asking no
queſtion for conſcience ſake, and that the rhetoricke of the
bramble ſhould ſilence the Vine and all the tree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Forreſt
(you know our meaning) you would never preſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the world
with ſuch a vaine, poore, ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ron, empty nothing, for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction
in ſo great and weighty a cauſe as this, which you
c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll <hi>A ſerious and faithfull repreſentation of the judgements of
Miniſters of the Goſpell within,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Your Letter ſtands, though faintly, upon four feet.</p>
            <p>1. The occaſions of your writing it.</p>
            <p>2. The mattere criminall contained therein, charged upon
the Generall and Councel of Warre.</p>
            <p>3. The grounds and reaſons of your charge proving the
ſame.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:116114:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:116114:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:116114:7"/>
            <p>4. Your Miniſterial advice and councel thereupon.</p>
            <p>That they are all ſo feeble as not able to beare up your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed
authority thereof, in the judgments of rational and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial
Readers, wil quickly appear; for,</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the occaſions of it, which were,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The ſeverall applications as well by writing as verb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll
meſſages, inviting the Miniſters of <hi>London,</hi> or ſome of them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
meete with the Officers of the Army in their conſultations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
of Religion, <hi>page</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>2. The refuſall of theſe Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited.</p>
            <p>3. The reaſons of this refuſall.</p>
            <p>From the firſt of theſe, may wee not behold as on the one
hand, the Chriſtian candor, ingenuity, and condiſcention
of the General and Councel of Warre, forgetting the many
falſe, notorious, and publique ſlanders of theſe men caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
them, from their pens and Pulpits from day to day, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring
(if it were poſſible) to defile and be-ſpatter that gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of honour which God put upon them, that they ſhould
apply themſelves; nay, make ſeveral applications of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
unto them, ſend to them, and write to them, &amp;c. So
on the other hand, the domineering, Lordly, and Prelatical
pride of theſe un-Chriſt-like <hi>Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> that
would not vouchſafe ſuch a condiſcention as to give them a
meeting; ſurely that Papal unction (which was by the ſpirit
from beneath powred forth upon the heads of the Popes of old
time, puſſing up their minds to that meaſure of pride, arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy,
and ſupercilliouſneſſe, as Kings and Princes with
their Wives and Children, muſt gladly, even with their hare
feet, attend their Holineſſes pleaſure day after day, before their
admiſſion) hath plentifully extended to the skirts of their
cloathing; theſe <hi>ſervi ſervorum dei,</hi> theſe Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,
theſe zealous and hot diſput<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> againſt the errours, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies,
and blaſphemies of the Army, cannot be prevailed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<hi>by ſeverall applications, by writing, by verball meſſages,</hi> to
adviſe, counſell, and direct them in matters of the greateſt
concernment to the whole Nation, to prevent the ſubject-matter
of their daily Pulpit-invectives againſt them, from the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116114:7"/>
power of tyranny, and the pride of the Clargy: <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> nos
Domine,</hi> they can <hi>lift up their voyces like a Trumpet</hi> In moſt
ſcandalon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> accuſations, ſlanderous defa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ations, and bitter
invectives, allarming people againſt them, but cannot he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed
withall, no not by <hi>ſeverall applications</hi> of ſeverall kinds
to adviſe and conſult, to direct or inſtruct in the greateſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
concerning the good or evill, ſaving or looſing the whole
Nation, is this; <hi>while you have opportunity to doe good to all:</hi>
and is this is vindication of your Miniſteriall function wherein
you ſo often glory?</p>
            <p>We Miniſters of the Goſpel within the Province of London, hold
it our duty as then to refuſe any ſuch meeting as was propoſed: ſo now
to give your Lordſhip and Councell the reaſons of that refuſail, leſt
by our ſilence we ſhould ſeeme to be wanting in that ingenuity and
candor which becomes all, but eſpecially the Miniſters of Jeſus
Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wee Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt within the Province of</hi> London:
what are the ſignes and tokens proving the ſame? your <hi>ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity
and candor which becomes the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent,
a teſtimony whereof you give by all your carriages as
to all men that obſerve your foot-ſteps: ſo eſpecially,</p>
            <p>Firſt, To the Army, calling them in your Pulpits a rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious
Army, a generation of vipers, a viprou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> brood, an
oppreſſing Army, an Army of Hereticks, a Schiſmaticall Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
an Army whoſe lives are not worth a prayer, and whoſe
deaths are not worth a teare; an Army, though conque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing,
yet they were not fit nor worthy to conquer; that wee had
been better without thoſe great victories, then to have them by
ſuch hands. Admirable <hi>ingenuity,</hi> unparallel'd <hi>candor,</hi> ſuch
ingenuity and candor appearing in Mr. <hi>Canton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cranford,</hi>
Mr. <hi>Caſe,</hi> Mr. <hi>Love,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> Mr. <hi>Tailor,</hi> and ſome others,
which did never appear in <hi>Peter, James,</hi> or <hi>John;</hi> yea, nor e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
in Jeſus Chriſt himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Your ingenuity and candor further appeares by
your ſubmiſſive and Chriſtian reſpects to authority, eſpecially
the Parliament: and as at all times, ſo chiefly when they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
not, though with the ruine of all, for your greatneſſe and
intereſt; then your Miniſterial <hi>ingenuity and candor</hi> doe appear
<pb facs="tcp:116114:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:116114:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:116114:9"/>
in all their glory, calling them (while they delay your work)
an apoſtatizing Parliament, a Covenant-breaking Parliament,
a Parliament at whoſe doors may be laid all the errors, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,
and blaſphemies of the times; a Parliament that hath
wrought a great Reformation amongſt us in Church &amp; State,
taking away High-commiſſion Court, Star-chamber, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel
Table, &amp;c. and bringing in the room thereof ſeveral Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees,
whoſe little fingers in way of oppreſſion, were heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
then the loins of the former Courts; a Parliament ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
Popery, Ceremonies, Crucifixes, Croſſes, Service-book,
&amp;c. and in the roome thereof giving liberty of Conſcience, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
called a curſed tolleration of errours, hereſies, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies,
and all manner of licentiouſneſſe; a Parliament that
hath taken away Ship-money, coat and conduct-money, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolies,
&amp;c. and in the roome thereof bringing in taxes, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſments,
free-quarters, and the heavy burthen and bondage
of Excize, which neither wee nor our Fathers were ever able
to beare: Is not this excellent Provinciall <hi>ingenuity and candor,</hi>
which further dazles mens eyes: and therefore,</p>
            <p>In the third place (for the ſame of your <hi>ingenuity and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor</hi>
is known to all men) doe not they further appear by your
abetting, countenancing, and encouraging violence and force
upon the two Houſes by a company of looſe, prophane, and
wicked fellowes at one time, as ſome of you did (for we would
not be underſtood of you all, many whereof are meerly drawn
in to the amazement of thoſe that read their names, though
not for lack of inconſiderateneſſe) falling in with the diſaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,
delinquent, and malignant party; and at another time
crying out, exclaiming, accuſing, arragning, and condemning
that very Army, which (from ſome of your own mouths it
hath been ſpoken) have beene inſtruments of the preſervation
of your very lives and liberties, the Lords battle-axe, and arm
of ſalvation to this Kingdome, and the intereſt of the Goſpel
and all honeſt men amongſt us, becauſe neceſſiatated upon
the perill of loſing the benefit of above 7. years warres, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering
all to return again into their old channell; yea, redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
the Nation to more intollerable bondage and ſlavery then
ever) they did ſecure the perſons of thoſe Members of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116114:9"/>
Commons Houſe that did moſt baſely promote, and end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
to bring about the Kings and Cavalliers moſt tyrannicall
and wicked deſign.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, For the ingenuity and candor of <hi>London</hi> Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers
is famous throughout the whole Kingdome; doth it not
further appeare, by ſetting the people at firſt againſt the King
and his party, firing mens ſpirits againſt him, charging him
with the guilt of the blood of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi>
conjuring men by all your devout and Miniſteriall artifice to
fight againſt him, &amp;c. And now having raiſed mens ſpirit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
a reſolution of requiring juſt and Scripturall ſatisfaction, that
blood may be avenged, and according to Gods expreſs word
expiated, to cry out in your Pulpits and Pamphlets, murther,
murther, and innocent blood, and the ſtaining the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
Religion with the blood of the King, &amp;c. Is not this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celling
<hi>ingenuity</hi> and rare <hi>candor?</hi> It you ſhall deny thy, I ſhal
ſhew you ſeverall of your owne bookes and Sermons, proving
both the one and the other: and for a taſt at preſent, take one
inſtance of a very zealous Paſter of your Catalogue, Mr. <hi>Chrè<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher
Love,</hi> Paſtor of <hi>Anne</hi> Alderſgate, when he was an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
man of <hi>Windſor</hi> Garriſon, preaching at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge,</hi> when
the treaty with the Kings and Parliaments Commiſſioners be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
there; read his words in his Sermon, called <hi>Englands Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper,</hi>
page 23. It would ſearch to the quick, to find <hi>one</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
King <hi>James,</hi> and Prince <hi>Henry</hi> his ſonne, came to a timely
death, yea or no: Some Parliaments <hi>have</hi> been but ſhort liv'd
when there was but a muttering, that enquiry ſhould be made
into their deaths. It would ſearch to the quick, to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>Rothel,</hi> and all the Proteſtants in it were not betrayed into
the hands of their Enemies, and by whom. It would goe to the
quick, to find out whether the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion was not ploured,
promoted, countenanced and contrived in <hi>England,</hi> and by
whom.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>page</hi> 32. The Lord heales a Land by cutting off
theſe diſtemper'd members that endanger the health of a Land;
it was the Lord that troubled <hi>Achan,</hi> and cut him off, becauſe
he troubled <hi>Iſrael!</hi> Oh that <hi>in this our State-Phyſicians would
reſemble God,</hi> to cut off thoſe from the Land who have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper'd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116114:10"/>
it; <hi>melius eſt ut pereat unus quam unitas.</hi> What is this
but to incence the people to an implacable ſpirit of revenge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the King? and was not this the tune of moſt of theſe
Subſcribers, though I cannot ſay ſo of them all, (ſome of
them being true to their principles of Cavall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>riſme from the
beginning) and yet now how doe theſe men ſpeake the very
language of <hi>Aſhdod,</hi> and out-ſtrip thoſe Miniſters of Jeſus
Chriſt too, (if ordination and Academicall education can
make them ſo) I meane Mr. <hi>Love's</hi> ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> as he cals the
ſonnes of <hi>Lavi,</hi> in <hi>page</hi> 31. of his ſaid Sermon, in calling
thoſe that continues their faithfulneſſe to the Kingdomes inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
againſt the late King and his tyranny, Traytos, Rebels,
and Murtherers, &amp;c. Is this the ingenuity and candor that
becomes the Miniſters of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt? But I
neede not goe farther then this very Pamphleticall Letter of
yours, and vindication, to finde out your <hi>ingenuity and candor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, You tell the world, <hi>that ſome of your brethren at one
conference with the Generall and ſome of his Councell, and at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
with ſome of his chief Officers, did manifeſt their diſlike of their
late actions,</hi> &amp;c. Was this <hi>ingenuity and candor</hi> either in your
Brethren or your ſelves, to make their private meetings and
conference a ground of a publique charge, and print it abroad
without conſent? Was this <hi>ingenuous and candid</hi> for ſome of
theſe Brethren only to publiſh the ſame without conſent of the
reſt? Was it <hi>ingenuous</hi> for you to print it without conſent of
all? Was it <hi>ingenuous</hi> for you to make your Brethrens onely
<hi>diſlike</hi> (we know not upon what grounds and arguments, not
one is declared (except diſtemper'd, jealous, and uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
thoughts againſt the Army) a ſufficient ground of your fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
the City and Countrey, Pulpits and Preſſes, againſt the
proceedings of Juſtice and Judgement amongſt us? Is it inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous
and candid for you to tell the Army, that the conſtant
judgement of Proteſtant Divines (with whom you doe fully
concur) is, that they diſclaime, deteſt, and abhor the
wicked and bloody tenets of Jeſuites concerning the oppoſing
of lawfull Magiſtrates by private perſons, and the murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
of Kings by any, &amp;c. As if the Parliament and Army
were no more an authority then a private ſingle perſon, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116114:10"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat their juſt proceeding againſt the King for his bloody and
wicked Government, was even a murthering the King? Doe
you not ſhew your ſelves ingenuous and candid as Miniſters of
Chriſt in the ſight of Heaven and Earth: would you not count
others that ſhould doe ſo, falſe, bold, pertenacious, ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous,
mutinous, ſeditious, rebellious fellows, if men of your
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſ-intereſt? Doth the Parliament, or Army, or any man of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſdome or reaſon, maintaine it lawfull with Jeſuites to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Kings? Will you ſay that all Proteſtant Divines hold it
unlawfull to depoſe, or capitally to deale with Tyrants and
Murtherers, if Kings and Princes? Though Doctor <hi>Burges</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndeed (and it may be ſome other of the quondam-Prelaticall
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ribe, that can face about with times and Intereſts) did ſo
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aintaine and hold, <hi>vid.</hi> Dr. <hi>Burges</hi> fire of the Sanctu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry, <hi>page</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>88. Yet you ſhall have an anſwer drawn from ſome of your
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wne parties labours proving the contrary: but if not, your
<hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>genuity and candor</hi> which you ſhew to the World, doe more
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>come Mountebanks then Miniſters; Juglers &amp; Jeſuits, then
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e faithfull diſpenſers of the word of truth: Is not this
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eer blinds to the people, to ſay all Divines that are Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nts
are againſt murthering of Kings, therefore Parliaments
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd people muſt not proceed againſt trayterous and murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous
Tyrants, that make no conſcience of ſhedding the blood
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thouſands and ten thouſands; yea hundreds of thouſands
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f poore innocent perſons and Proteſtant people, for the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>action
of their meere filthy luſts, and wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>Againe, was it not an <hi>ingenuous, candid,</hi> and brotherly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n you (becauſe Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> did Chriſtianly adviſe you to <hi>forbear
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſtirre up the people to ſedition</hi> (for ſo you have endeavoured, if
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here can be any ſuch thing in P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lpits) <hi>leaſt Souldiers ſhould doe
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou a miſchiefe, and you may thanke your ſelves,</hi> aſſuring you that
<hi>if a third Warre be ſtirr'd up, they will</hi> give no quarter, &amp;c.) to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>print him to the World as if he threatned the people, and was
the great man of their trouble and diſtemper, that if it was
poſſible he might not walke the ſtreets in ſafety?</p>
            <p>Againe, was it not yet more of your <hi>ingenuity and candor</hi> to
aſſert ſeverall notorious falſities and untruths, and to give
your Readers a cluſter of theſe bitter grapes together, as to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116114:11"/>
               <hi>page</hi> 6. of your Vindicationiin the margin;<note place="margin">Page 6. of your Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> where you
ſay that the agreement of the people was <hi>the ſame for ſubſtance,</hi>
with an agreement of ſome in the Army, declared againſt by
the Parliament in <hi>December,</hi> 1647. There is one untruth,
that becauſe, <hi>that,</hi> therefore <hi>this,</hi> (being the ſame in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
with that, at leaſt in the matter of it) was then decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
againſt by both Houſes, and condemned heretofore by
the Generall and his Councell of Warre, there is one untruth
within another.</p>
            <p>Again, You ſay that <hi>one of the ſouldiers was ſhot to death for
promoting it;</hi> this is firſt, a moſt notorious untruth, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
a moſt injurious charging the Army with the blood
of that man, the man that was ſhot to death, was not as all
ſo much a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> queſtioned for promoting that agreement, or (as
ſome of the Souldiers affirme) did at all promote that agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
but being ſent with his Company by the Generall to
<hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> did with others make a mutiny, reſiſted, and
beate their Officers, tooke away the Colours from their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne,
beate him with his owne Colours, for which this fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
that was ſhot to death, being found moſt guilty, was
condemned and executed, and yet you have the boldneſſe and
confidence (you would call it in us) the face and impudence
to aſſert it as a truth to the very teeth of thoſe that know the
contrary; and all this in the profeſſion of ſuperlative <hi>ingen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity
and candor,</hi> even ſuch <hi>as becomes the Miniſters of the Goſpel, and
Embaſſadors of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Were theſe things ſubſcribed and
aſſerted by <hi>ſome</hi> of you, whoſe tongues are famous for ſlander<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
as Mr. <hi>Cranford,</hi> who once either did or ſhould have ſate in the
ſtoole of repentance even at the <hi>Exchange</hi> for his ſlanderous
forgeries; or Mr. <hi>Cauton,</hi> who makes it but a ſmall thing to
ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t his viprous language, of Traitors, Rebels, generation
of Vipers, murtherers, &amp;c. againſt thoſe with whom hee is
not worthy to be n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>med for piety and prudence, it was not
much to be wond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed at: but that Mr. <hi>Gataker,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fuller,</hi> Mr.
<hi>Blackewell.</hi> Mr. <hi>Haviland,</hi> Mr. <hi>Manton,</hi> ſhould ſubſcribe ſuch
notorious falſities, argues that indeed the beſt of men are but
men at beſt, and that the wiſeſt are ſometimes weake; where
i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the wiſdome of the wiſe, and the underſtanding of the aged?
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116114:11"/>
Is not this the high way to prejudice your Miniſtery, and
provoke unto contempt and ſcorn?</p>
            <p>Again, (For there is ſcarce a leaſe in your Letter, wherein
your <hi>ingenuity and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndor</hi> doe not appear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the like colours)
you aſſert another groſſe untruth (to call it a miſtake, we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to
miſtake its name) in the beginning and threſhold of your Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
which you make the occaſion thereof, and that is, that <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rall
application<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by writing and verball meſſages were made unto
you to meete with the Officers and ſome of the Army in their conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
about matters of Religion,</hi> which after you ſay was on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to contribute your aſſiſtance in proſecution of what they had
undertaken before, informing your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaders as if you were
ſent meerly to confirme and ratifie, aſſiſt and further that which
they had wickedly begun before, and not at all to debate and
conſult about the lawfulneſſe of any of their wayes to give or
receive ſatisfaction therein, and you that know the truth of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he whole matter, are not you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſciences ſmitten within
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou for miſ-informing your Brethren, and drawing them in
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſubſcribe ſuch groſſe untruth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Can you face ſuch a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure
as you quote, when you ſay you are <hi>comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nded to cry aloud
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> life up your voyees as trumpets to ſhew the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>opl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,
and the houſe of Jacob their ſinnes.</hi> Were not you ſolicited
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd invited to come unto them, and that with expreſſions to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his purpoſe, that all honeſt intereſts might be ſatisfied, and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot yours neglected; were not your ſeverall objections anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
why you denied to come, again and again? did not ſome
of you urge this a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one reaſon againſt your comming, that
they had agreed upon their way, and were reſolved hereupon
ſay you what you could: and therefore leſt you ſhould be
looked upon as concurring with them, you denied to goe:
and were not you anſwered to this purpoſe, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
was done, if you could ſhew ſatisfactory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againſt
the ſame, all that was done ſhould be as if nothing at all had
been done; ſpeake your conſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nces, are not theſe things ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
why then doe you ſtaine the profeſſion and function of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
the Goſpel with ſuch noto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ious falſhoods: Are you no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
herein like unto Kings and Princes, that proſecute the greateſt
deſignes againſt Religion and Liberty under the colour of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116114:12"/>
preateſt profeſſions and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roteſtations of promot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
and the other? Is this your Chriſtian <hi>ingenuity and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
this your <hi>abſtaining from all appearance of evill? and your having
no fellowſhip with the unfruitfull works of darkeneſſe, but rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving
them?</hi> were there ever ſo many untruths ſo ſubſcribed
before? The true reaſon of your refuſing to come unto them,
you ſomewhat tenderly, but clearly declare, <hi>viz.</hi> their no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
obſervation of that which you ſeeme to conceive to bee the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
true diſtance from you; they came not propounding their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
unto you in ſuch a way as <hi>was ſuitable for private perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
have propounded, and for Miniſters of the Goſpel to have reſolved.</hi>
Oh high ſtrain <hi>of ingenuity and candor becomming the Miniſter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of
the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt!</hi> Is this to take hold of all occaſions of
doing good? Is this to preach the Word in ſeaſon and out of
ſeaſon? Is this like Jeſus Chriſt? Did hee give commiſſion to
his Diſciples to goe no where but unto ſuch as ſhould enqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
after them in a regular way? Is this that humility, ſweetne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>ingenuity and candor</hi> becomming Miniſters? Once more yet,
concerning your <hi>ingenuity and candor</hi> in the title of your Letter,
you ſay it <hi>is a repreſentation of Miniſters of the Goſpel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
Province of London:</hi> And among your ſubſcriptions I finde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Joſhuah Kerby,</hi> Miniſter of the Word, but I pray of what
place; in what Pariſh is he either Paſtor, Miniſter, or Preacher
within the Province of <hi>London?</hi> Doe you begin, conti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>,
and conclude with ſuch ample teſtimonie of your <hi>ingenuity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
candor?</hi> Had you been as ingenuous and candid as you would
ſeeme to be, you would have ſaid <hi>Nicholas Profet,</hi> Miniſter of
the Word at <hi>Foſters,</hi> alias, at <hi>Marlborough</hi> in <hi>Sommerſet-ſhire</hi> (if
I be not deceived) and <hi>Stanly Gowre,</hi> Miniſter as <hi>Martins</hi>
Ludgate, <hi>alias,</hi> Paſtor of <hi>Dorcheſter</hi> in <hi>Dorcet-ſhire</hi> (if I be not
deceived) you would have written <hi>John Hulke,</hi> Preacher at
<hi>Alhallows</hi> upon the wall, immediately after <hi>Andrew Janeway,</hi>
Paſtor of the ſame place, and not put downe 27. betweene,
that the Reader may preſume ſo many diſtinct Pariſhes as you
place Miniſters; and have told us whether this wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that <hi>Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
of <hi>Eſſex</hi> which was ſequeſtred, yea or no: and in the Title of
your Vindication you would not have put in that particle of
univerſality; <hi>A vindication of THE Miniſters of the Goſpel is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116114:12"/>
and about London,</hi> fetching ſuch a circumference, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in not a third part of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
and in the ſubſcription of the ſame Vindication, you would
not have gone ſo far as <hi>Walſingham</hi> in the Biſhoprick of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
for <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Devere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x,</hi> and palliate the ſame by calling
him late Miniſter at <hi>Andrews,</hi> Holborne: Neither would you
have ſtain'd your reputation with the mention of <hi>Thomas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
Paſtor of <hi>Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ins-Outwich,</hi> carryed from <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lym<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th</hi> for
his notrious D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nquency, and worth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly ſequeſtred for the
ſame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> no more now (if poſſible) of your <hi>ingenuity and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>—you proceede to matter of charge againſt the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
<hi>page</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>It is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> known what attempts of late <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
practice againſt lawfull Authority, eſpecially by your late <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> publiſhed in oppoſition to the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ceedings
of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alſo by ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>zing and impriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ning the Kings Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
without the knowledge and conſent of Parliament, and by that
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> offered to the Members of it, many of
whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to us to bee man of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> worth and integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<hi>&amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>It hath beene already ſufficiently replyed by way of anſwer
to the paper of the Armies Propoſals of the ſixth of <hi>December,</hi>
laſt, in ſeverall other expreſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from the Army, <hi>viz.</hi> in a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance come forth after thoſe Propoſals, a Declaration af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
that Remonſtrance, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Anſwer of the generall
Councell of Officers of the Army to the Demands of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rable
the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> all which containe the
grounds &amp; reaſons of thoſe <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tempts of late put in practiſe by the
Army againſt lawfull authority,</hi> &amp;c. But you have got the ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
of ſtopping your ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> like dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Adder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>vid.</hi> The humble an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of the general coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the Commons of England, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding ſome Members, p. 2.</note> to any argument of
ſatisfaction, and ſtill to inſiſt upon the Armies proceeding<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
againſt the Members which themſelves doe acknowledge, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
conſidered, <hi>irregular, and not juſtifiable, but by honeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
for publique good, and an extraordinary neceſſity for the ſame
end, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ding them thereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though your eares have beene often heaten with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
vindicating ſuch a neceſſity, whereunto you have been<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
mute; yet doe you your ſelves judge, whether in caſe either by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116114:13"/>
the artifice of the King and his wicked party, malignant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
bars ſhould be brought into the Houſe, or thoſe that were
formerly againſt the King, becauſe their intereſt and his were
inconſiſtent, ſhould (having received ſatisfaction in that
point) make their owne advantages in a corrupt cloſure with
the King, endeavouring to bring him in upon his own terms
without ſatisfaction or ſecurity to the Kingdome, as they did
upon his owne Meſſage of the 12. of <hi>May,</hi> 1647. and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
to diaband the Army, protecting the 11. Members im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached
of Treaſon, endeavouring with them to raiſe a ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
Warre, liſting Reformadoes, altering the <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>London,</hi>
imb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>zeling the 200000. pound appointed for the relief of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
in ſuch endeavours, countenancing, abetting, and
partaking with that tumultuous violence of the Apprentic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
and others againſt both Houſes of Parliament, driving awa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
the Speakers and many faithfull Members, <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1647 ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
up a new Speaker, giving large power, and paſſing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
Ordinances for the raiſing of a new Warre, arming Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants,
ſtirring up the City, authorizing <hi>Maſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
all in proſecution of the treaſonable Engagement, of
bringing in the King upon his own termes, and (all this bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
through the grace of God by the courage, conſtancy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
and faithfulneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of this (your great eye-ſore) Army.) Then
againe trying a new feate, <hi>viz.</hi> contriving, promoting, and
aſſiſting tumultuous Petitioners for a Perſonall Treaty, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſponding
with the rebellious inſurrections in <hi>Kent, Eſſex,
&amp;c.</hi> The revolted ſhips, Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> the <hi>Scots</hi> Army in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vading
this Kingdome, that ſo the Army may be ſhattered
into ſeverall diſperſions, precipitating thereby the Kingdome
again into a new, bloody, and fierce Warre, hazarding the
cauſe of all the former troubles, and a totall conqueſt of the
whole Kingdome; during which ſecond War, many of the
faithfull Members being employed abroad; others diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
through malignant tumults about the City, to forbeare
their attendance; theſe Members formerly impeached and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
Tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tors were recalled, and others that were elected in
their roome caſt out of the Houſe. Votes for no further Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes
to the King recalled, and made void, voted to treate
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116114:13"/>
with the King upon ſuch Propoſitions as himſelf ſhould make,
exempt from Juſtice the capitall Leaders in the laſt Summers
Wars, by an hypocriticall voting many of them to be baniſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t,
fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng the reſt, &amp;c. reſolving the Kings re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation with free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>,
ſafety and honour: I ſay doe you your ſelves judge
whether (all theſe things with many more) being true, they
were not neceſſitated to doe that which you call <hi>putting at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts
in practice againſt lawfull Authority, viz.</hi> ſeizing thoſe
Members, although many whereof were knowne to you
(though to few elſe but Malignant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and men of your intereſt)
<hi>to be men of emminent worth and integrity.</hi> Suppoſe the Army
(who are bound by their Commiſſions, by their Oaths, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations,
Vowes and Covenants; by all the intereſt, peace,
and liberties of the Kingdome, to bring Delinquents to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igne
puniſhment) ſhould finde their grand Enemies (againſt
whom they formerly did engage in open Field) in the Houſe;
or that thoſe in the Houſe, formerly faithfull as <hi>Hotham</hi> and
many others, were turn'd as had, as baſe, as malignant a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Hotham</hi> did prove, and every way the ſame with Malignants,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould they let them alone becauſe ſitting in the Houſe? I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>awfull to kill and deſtroy them, if they goe about to deſtroy
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Field, and not ſo much as interrupt them though
they ſhould enſlave us, ruine and deſtroy us by a law?</p>
            <p>And againe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whereas you ſpeake ſo much of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
authority, and fill the ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of your Auditors from you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
Pulpits from day to day with rebellizing the Army for their
late proceedings againſt the Members, muſtering up theſe
Scriptures, teaching and preſſing duty to authority which the
Prelaticall party did formerly uſe againſt you,<note place="margin">Prov. 24. 21. Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s 3. 1. Rom. 13. 1, 2.</note> as that of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon:
P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e thou God and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing: Pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them in minde to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
to Principalities and powers. Let every ſoule be ſubject to the
higher powers,</hi> &amp;c. Yet we heard not of theſe things from you
when the mutinous Apprenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es and others offered violence
upon the Houſes formerly ſpoken of, no noiſe then of ſuch
Scriptures, no <hi>putting m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n in minde to ſubject to Principalities
and powers;</hi> no ſuch word as <hi>let every ſoule be ſubject to the higher
powers,</hi> &amp;c. As if theſe Scriptures were ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>led ſince that time.
Can you preſume that men are ſo blind, dull, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116114:14"/>
not to obſerve ſuch partiall and crafty handling of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turer,
word and will of God; doe not theſe practiſes of yours<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttle and eſtabliſh atheiſme, irrel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gion, and profanen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
men, making them to looke upon Religion, the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,
the Word of God, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon a meere pee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of jugling,
cheating, and deceiving the World: and ſhould we take your
counſell which you give us from the words of <hi>Solomon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ddle
not with them that are given to change,</hi> we ſhould all turne S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſts
from you and your wayes, who have beene as full of
changes at the Vanes of your Steeples; one while ſtirring up
the people againſt the King, and for the Parliament, writing
Books, anſwering objections, and uſing all manner of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours
that way (that ſo the Biſhops may be dethroned, and
you advanced) witneſſe many of your Sermons preached before
the Houſes and elſe-where: another while ſtirring up the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
againſt the Parliament, and for the King (left the <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents</hi>
ſhould hinder your advance) as you did of late in
your Prayers and Preaching, expreſſing greater malignity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the <hi>Parliament</hi> and their party, and greater <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for
the King and his intereſt, then thoſe very Miniſters whoſe
very places you poſſeſe, they being ſequeſtred and caſt out
for the tenths of that <hi>Anti-parliamentary</hi> malignancy which
you have vented, and indeed this is according to the example
of your Fathers before you; for it was generally obſerved of
the Clergy of olde, that in <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> time they were
firſt for the Popes ſupremacy, and then with the King for the
Kings; With <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth they were Proteſtants, with
Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> Papiſts againe; With Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> they fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
about, and of 9400. promotions, not too of them ſtood
firm: Nay does not our owne age give ſufficient teſtimony of
the Clergies changes; nay are not many of your ſelves living
inſtances thereof, have not you been for Biſhops, and againſt
Biſhops, for Common-prayer, for Geremonies, and againſt
them? Have you not ſworne and ſubſcribed, and ſubſcribed
and ſworn over and over, againe and againe, conformity and
ſubjection hereunto, and yet caſt away all, and entered into
Vowes and Covenants againſt all? Can Dr. <hi>Burges,</hi> Maſter
<hi>Cauton,</hi> and ſeverall others of you deny this, and yet now
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116114:14"/>
adviſe us not to <hi>meddle with them that are given to change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay page 5. <hi>It was deemed a horrible violation of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges
of Parliaments in the King, to come to ſeize upon the five
Members in the beginning of this Parliament.</hi> And you quote the
opinion of the Houſe for that purpoſe in their Order of the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
of <hi>January,</hi> 1641. What violation of their priviledges then
muſt this needs be, ſo and ſo aggravated to ſeize upon many,
&amp;c. I may anſwer you by telling you that you never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
that Order of the Houſe in aggravating of the Appren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orcing of the Houſe the laſt yeare: and to give you any other
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſwer, were but to beate the aire, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are like to heare
no reply to it, having the art of neglecting all that hath been
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>poken by way of ſatisfaction from the Army to this purpoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd inſiſting ſtill upon matter of fact, as if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thereof
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad been given in juſtification.</p>
            <p>You tell us that <hi>both Houſes of Parliament are (joyntly conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed
with the King) intruſted with the ſupreame Authority of the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ingdome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 6.</note> I deſire to know what you meane by the <hi>King,</hi> his
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſon or his <hi>Authority?</hi> If his <hi>Perſon,</hi> then have we been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>,
and you the cauſe of it, ſtirring us up hereunto; If you
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Authority,</hi> then let your Readers reviſe your Letter
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and they will ſee you ſay nothing, but (according
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your cuſtome) blinde the people, which is not like that
<hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and candor becomming Miniſters of the Goſpell of Jeſus
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the maine thing you inſiſt upon is the buſineſſe of the
Proteſtation, Vow, and Covenant, and the Solemn League &amp;
Covenant; by theſe ſacred gin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (as you uſe them) you preſume
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Scots</hi> Commiſſioners heretofore) to catch us all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our net, doing little ſervice thereby, except to draw men into
diſhonorable thoughts of them: and as you doe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our Function (of it ſelfe honourable, and of God) yet you
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake it contemptible and vile; even ſo in reference to theſe
(of themſelves juſt and good) <hi>you,</hi> and chiefly <hi>you render</hi> them
<hi>as an Almanack out of date;</hi> for what doe you make eſpecially
of the Covenant, but (as ſome doe of the Scriptures) a noſe
of wax, making it to ſerve all their opinions) to maintain all
intereſts; for doe not all men know that you were the men
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116114:15"/>
preſſing people to oppoſe, with-ſtand, and fight againſt the
King, and that upon penalty of breaking the <hi>COVENANT</hi>
of God, the <hi>COVENANT</hi> of peace, conjuring men as
they would anſwer it before the Lord, as they would not be
counted <hi>COVENANT</hi> breakers, Truce-breakers, falſe to
the <hi>COVENANT</hi> of their God, &amp;c. to goe out to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the Lords Enemies, to fight the Lords battles, &amp;c.
And now againe doe not you make the <hi>Covenant</hi> to ſerve the
Malignants intereſt, and the late Kings intereſt, by preſſing
that article of the <hi>Covenant</hi> of preſerving the Kings perſon,
honour and dignity, &amp;c. and that with the ſame ſtraines of
ſanctimony, <hi>viz.</hi> by calling it <hi>the Oath of God, the Covenant
of God,</hi> making Malignants jeere and laugh at you, and thoſe
that did firſt hate the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and ſome that never yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
the <hi>Covenant,</hi> to plead and argue our <hi>Covenant-breaking,</hi> &amp;c.
Did not ſome of you demand, <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this preſerving the perſon of the
King by cutting off his head,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Yenkin.</hi> Mr. <hi>Love.</hi> Mr. <hi>Caſe.</hi> Mr. <hi>Canton,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>by murthering him, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the
Land with the blood of their Soveraigne,</hi> &amp;c. And did not the
King heretofore, and Malignants with the like reaſon, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
of you, <hi>is this to preſerve the perſon of the King, to fight
againſt him even in pitch'd Battles; in this to maintaine his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
and dignity, to charge him with all the blood that hath been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
&amp;c. But more particularly touching the <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> May 5.
1641. the <hi>Vow and Covenant</hi> made afterwards, and <hi>the ſolemn
League and Covenant</hi> made after that: From theſe mountaine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
you ſtrive (though with very much devotion as <hi>Bala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> once
did) to curſe the Army and <hi>Parliament,</hi> when loe your curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
prove ſo only to their Authors, and (like the Conjurers
in the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> when the name of <hi>Jeſus</hi> whom
<hi>Paul</hi> preached was uſed as a piece of inchantment to diſpoſſeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
the ſonnes of <hi>Sceva,</hi> a Jew, were overcome even by that ſpirit
whom they would conjure to come out of them) theſe, <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation,
Vow,</hi> and <hi>League</hi> which you ſo preſſe, not regarding
all that hath been ſaid again and again by way of anſwer, as
ſuppoſing that when argument, Scripture, and reaſon can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
help you, yet the <hi>Proteſtation, Vow,</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> will
doe it; theſe like the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> reeds run into your ſides, and
do no ſervice at all for you, but diſcover your nakedneſſe; for</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:116114:15"/>
            <p>Firſt, For the Proteſtation, that paſſage concerning the
late <hi>King</hi> (the main thing you drive at by quoting the ſame)
can meane only a <hi>lawfull</hi> defence (<hi>according to the duty of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance)
of his royall Perſon, honour, and eſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, We proteſted to defend his Perſon <hi>according to the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of Allegiance,</hi> whereby wee were tyed to his juſt authority,
and not abſtractively to his Perſon, if acting contrary and
deſtructive to his juſt authority, as you know he did.</p>
            <p>2. Again, our Allegiance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> no further <hi>lawfull</hi> then relative
to the kingdome whereunto even he himſelfe was tyed in Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance.</p>
            <p>3. Again, Allegiance if relative, binds no further then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the lawes of relation, and relations are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>,
and the roote of all obli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ations; which whether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
all or otherwiſe, yet when on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> party ſhall ſeeke the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion
of the other, the other may juſtly claime a receſſe ſo far
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> abſolute preſervation require<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>4. Again, The Proteſtation is not only for the defence of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Majeſties Perſon:</hi> but the ſentence is complex, and takes
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his <hi>honour and eſtate,</hi> the impairing of the one, and the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtring
or ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing of the other, hath been (without ſcandal
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it ſpoken to you) the uſe &amp; application of your own former
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>octrine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, no party in the Kingdome having more ſtained
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>honour,</hi> if declaring his wickedneſſe can do it by Preſſe and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ulpit-worke then your ſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; and if his <hi>eſtate</hi> had beene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
for the <hi>defence</hi> and preſervation of <hi>his Perſon</hi> in your
preſent apoſtate ſence, all the benefit (that I know of) that
you ſhould have thereby, would be the receiving of your tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
before your time, for your new friends (Malignan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>)
are in your debt, and was it not for your Enemies (the Armie)
they would quickly pay you.</p>
            <p>5. Wee did likewiſe proteſt for <hi>the defence of the power and
priviledges of Parliament, the lawfull rights and liberties of
the Subjects</hi> as well as the <hi>Perſon of the King;</hi> If <hi>the Perſon of the
King</hi> be engaged againſt the <hi>priviledges of Parliament and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
of the Subject,</hi> or the Parliament themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges
againſt <hi>the lawfull rights and liberties of the Subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts,</hi> the
Proteſtation cannot be obligatorie unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:116114:16"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>rights and liberties of the Subjects</hi> being the great end of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Parliament, muſt proſtrate both King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
the King and Parliament as ſuch, having no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo much
as their being, much leſſe priviledges againſt <hi>the lawfull right<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
and liberties of the Subjects,</hi> ſo that by the Proteſtation (the
<hi>greater</hi> being (of duty) to be profes'd before the <hi>leſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi>) if the
Perſon of the King, or priviledges of Parliament ſtand in the
way like a Lyon and a Beare to devour <hi>the lawfull rights and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties
of the Subjects</hi>) we are bound to know neither King nor
Parliament, but the people (the root of them both) better the
<hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould periſh then the people.</p>
            <p>6. We are bound by this Proteſtation to maintain and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
the <hi>King, Parliament,</hi> and <hi>People</hi> in a lawfull manner,
<hi>ſo farre as lawfully we may,</hi> which refers unto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
defence; while the King was in Perſon againſt the Parliament,
we were by this Proteſtation to defend the Parliament &amp; Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
though with the hazard of the King (otherwiſe you have
preached falſe Doctrine to us) if the King and Parliament
ſhould engage againſt the people, we are by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
tyed to preſerve the people though with the hazard of both;
when the Parliament engaged againſt the King in a milita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y
way, we were not tyed by this Proteſtation to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to def<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d
his perſon: If the Parliament engage againſt the King in a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
judiciary way, was were neither obliged by this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation
to reſcue the Kings Perſon againſt ſuch procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.</p>
            <p>7. We proteſted by all <hi>good meanes and wayes to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne
puniſhment all ſuch as ſhall either by farce, proctiſe, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels,
plots, conſpiracies, doe any thing to the contrary of any
thing contained in the Proteſtation.</hi> If then the King himſelfe,
or the Parliament in the ſeverall Members thereof ſhall <hi>either
by force, practiſe, councels, plots, conſpiracies, or otherwiſe</hi>
doe things contrary to the great end (the very ſpirit and life of
this Proteſtation) viz. <hi>the lawfull rights and liberties of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi>
the Subjects are bound by this Proteſtation <hi>by all good
wayes and meanes</hi> (and God doth not leave a people without
any grounds of ſelfe-preſervation) to bring to condign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment
<hi>both King and Parliament,</hi> none being here excepted.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:116114:16"/>
            <p>8. <hi>And laſtly, we proteſt that</hi> we will neither for hope, feare,
nor other reſpect, relinquiſh this Promiſe, Vow, and Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Now let the World judge, who it is that doth violate this
Proteſtation ſo as you doe; doe you not cry up the Perſon of
the King without any reference to the ſafety, peace, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties
of the people; doe not you rail out in the Pulpits as the
Prelaticall party did in the beginning of this Warre, Traitors,
Rebels, ſummoning up all thoſe Scriptures which they like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
did (as if they were added but as yeſterday to the Text)
<hi>My ſonne feare thou God and the King, meddle not with them that
are given to change, and he is the Lords Anoynted, and wilt thou
ſay to the King what doſt thou?</hi> Did you plead for the <hi>Kings
Perſon</hi> before, as you doe now? Why then did you ſtir up m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n
to fight againſt him? Did you plead for his <hi>honour and eſtate</hi>
before as now; why then did you ſo repreſent him to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
in your Pulpits from day to day? Doe you <hi>maintaine and
defend the rights and liberties of the Subjects;</hi> why then doe you
brand them with the name of Rebels and Traitors, that did
not lay down the ſword at the feete of the late King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
at their bare command, before any ſecurity at all gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
for the preſervation thereof? <hi>Doe you ende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vour to bring
Delinquents to condign puniſhment;</hi> why then doe you charge
thoſe that have brought him, whom your ſelves and the
Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> have charged for the greateſt Delinquent,
guilty of the blood of hundreds of thouſands of Proteſtants,
the bloudieſt man under Heaven) for Murtherers, Traitors,
Rebbels, as Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> Mr. <hi>Caſe, Mr. Love,</hi> Maſter
<hi>Cauton</hi> have done, calling the offering up of the moſt accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
and fatteſt ſacrifice unto Juſtice that ever was offered in
this Kingdome, <hi>the ſtaining of the Land with the blood of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign,
the imbruing our hands with our Soveraigns blood;</hi> yea,
<hi>murthering our King,</hi> ſtriving thereby if poſſible, to ſtir up the
people to cut the throates of the Parliament, Armie, and
high Court of Juſtice, and to ſheath each neighbors ſword in
his brothers bowels, &amp; yet you think your ſelves wrong'd to be
called Incendiaries? Have you endeavored <hi>to preſerve the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
and peace between the three Kingdomes of</hi> England, Scotland,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116114:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:116114:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:116114:18"/>
               <hi>and</hi> Ireland; How is it then that ſome of you even in Pulpits
have prayed for the good ſucceſſe of thoſe <hi>Scots</hi> that invaded
this Kingdome with an Armie of wicked and prophane men
the laſt yeare, breaking all Leagues, Covenants, Compacts
between the two Nations, and ſo voted by this Kingdome?
Have you <hi>neither for hope, feare, nor other reſpect, relinquiſhed
this promiſe, Vow, and Proteſtation;</hi> how is it then that you
are ſo ſhoffling, changing, and uncertaine, for the King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
and againſt the King, for the Parliament, and againſt the
Parliament, for the Army, and againſt the Army, for Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
and againſt Juſtice, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>king your viciſſitudes and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings
up and downe the ſubject-matter of ſcorne, contempt,
and deriſion both of your perſons and Function.</p>
            <p>Again, Whereas you mention the Vow and Covenant, you
might have indeed ſhewed <hi>your ingenuity and candor bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mming
the Miniſters of the Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to have taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
of that which was the maine end of that Vow and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
contained in theſe words; That <hi>I will according to my
power and vocation asſiſt the Forces raiſed and continued by both
Houſes of Parliament againſt the Forces raiſed by the King without
their conſent.</hi> Have you perform'd this Vow and Covenant
made and taken <hi>in the preſence of Almighty God the ſearcher of all
hearts, with a true intention to perform the ſame as you ſhall anſwer
at the great day, when the ſecrets of all hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts ſhall be diſcloſed:</hi>
What meanes then your lowing and bleating in the cares of the
people from day to day, ſtirring up the City and Countrey if
it be poſſible, to break <hi>the Forces raiſed and continued by both
Houſes of Parliament,</hi> requiring them <hi>in the name of the Lord to
riſe up as one man</hi> againſt that rebellious Army, aſſuring them
that God hath given it unto you that they ſhall not proſper,
but be broken in pieces comming againſt <hi>London,</hi> as once that
Army was which came againſt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and venturing the
credite of your Function upon your paſſionat tongue; affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
that if this comes not to paſſe, the Lord hath not ſpoken
by you as one of you affirmed; and if <hi>deliverance comes not by
you</hi> (ſpeaking to your Auditors) <hi>God will bring it in ſome other
way:</hi> and ſince that God hath given moſt ample teſtimony a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
you, by bleſſing that Army which you have curſed from
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:116114:18"/>
Pulp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to Pulpit in the name of the Lord, againſt whom you
begg'd, and prayed, and went, and raiſ'd up the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
groanes of your women-audience by your pathetick inveſtiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
while they happily have been fighting in blood, and many of
them expiring and breathing out their lives to ſave you from
apparent ruine and deſtruction, making ſome of your owne
party more Chriſtian and ingentious then your ſelves to bleſſe
God for them, acknowledging their own miſtakes and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
in their former oppoſing them; yea, and the whole
Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> to acknowledg the ſame, and to give a
candid and thankfull teſtimonie of them: and ſince that time
have not ſome of you prayed God to forgive the cowardice
of the City, that they did not take hold of the opportunity
of riſing up againſt the Army, admoniſhing them to be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
for it; As Mr. <hi>Jenkin</hi> before the Lord Major and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<hi>February</hi> 4. at Mercers Chappell, eſpecially that they
did neglect the opportunity for feare of Reformation, fearing
that a rigid Presbytery would be ſet up, they choſe rather to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtill; urging, that becauſe they neglected the government of
Jeſus Chriſt in the Church, they ſhall have no government
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the State (yet ſtroaking that party that was hopefully firme
to them) acknowledging that there were ſome that did keep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
the Covenant of their God, and were loyall to their late So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign,
and zealous for the government of Jeſus Chriſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuating
that the Parliament and Army, and Court of Juſtice
were guilty of the blood of the King, of breaking the hedge
of Government, of levelling mens eſtates, of ſedition, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
and rebellion, &amp;c. Is this your keeping the Vow and
Covenant which you here make mention of? Is this your <hi>aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
the Forces raiſed and continued by both Houſes of Parliament
againſt the Forces raiſed by the King?</hi> Were there ever ſuch ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
to the Parliaments Army in all the Kingdome as your
ſelves? Did not your very Sermons and prayers tend to little
elſe all the laſt Summer, then to breake the Forces raiſed up by
the Parliament? But the truth is, your folly is made known
unto all men, and you ſhall proceed no further; your P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pit
language of this nature is of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> uſe, except it be to the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
forth contempt upon your own heads.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:116114:19"/>
            <p>But the maine thing you inſiſt upon is the ſolemn Leagu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
and Covenant; this indeed ſerves you at every turne, when
all things elſe, when Scripture and reaſon, civility, juſtice and
honeſty leave you, you make <hi>the Solemn League and Covenant</hi>
to goe along with you, uſing it as you doe the holy Scriptures
themſelves, diſpoſſeſſing them of their true, naturall, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine
meaning; and (as Satan once aſſumed <hi>Samuels</hi> body to
deceive) you ſpirit them with your own opinion. Hence it is,
that when you were for the Parl. againſt the K. &amp; his Forces,
you ſtirr'd up the people with Scriptures, <hi>Curſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yee Meroz,</hi> &amp;c.
When your intereſt (your great Commander) bids you fac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
about, or makes peace with your Adverſary, and it may be
liſts you under his Colours; then (like mercenary ſouldiers
that ſights for money on either ſide) you engage againſt your
<hi>quondam</hi> party, and run to the Magazine of the Scriptures to
furniſh your ſelves with weapons (making them like thoſe
Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>treyes that indifferently ſell arms to their friends or foes)
then you cry out, <hi>feare thou God and the King: Let every ſoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
he ſubject,</hi> &amp;c. When the Prelaticall party ſtood in your way,
then you ſummon'd up all the Scriptures that you could come
at, relating to the wickedneſſe of ſuperſtition, Idolatry, and
of Prophets that tell lies in the name of the Lord; if on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
hand (the Prelates removed) you ſit not in their ſeats un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
a new notion; then you ſummon up the other ſtraine of
Scriptures, relating to the ſins of the people, in contemning
the Prophets of the Lord that deſpiſe his Meſſengers, &amp;c. Juſt
ſo you deale with the Covenant: when the Prelaticall party
oppoſeth you, then you run to that Article of the Solemne
League and Covenant, which engageth <hi>againſt Popery, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,
Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops; &amp;c.</hi> When a contrary party
ſtands in your way, and doe not conform to your Diſcipline,
and bow down to your ſheafe, then you pay them with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Article, engaging our endeavours for <hi>preſervation of the
reformed Religion in the Church of Scotland, in doctrine, worſhip,
diſcipline and government,</hi> &amp;c. If the Kings party lifts up a Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard
againſt you, then you ſtirre up the people from another
Article of the Covenant, engaging <hi>the diſcovery of all ſuch as
have beene: or ſhall be, Incendiaries, Malignants, or evill inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116114:19"/>
by hindering thereformation of Religion,</hi> and thoſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ges
obliging <hi>the preſervation of the rights and priviledges of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ament,</hi>
&amp;c. If the Parliament ſtand in your way, and joyning
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith the contrary party, may hopefully help, you ſlye to tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt and article of the Covenant, engaging for the <hi>preſervation
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> defence of the Kings Majeſties perſon and Authority,</hi> &amp;c. As
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Scripture in the ſeverall vein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s thereof, and the Solemne
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ague and Covenant in all the Articles thereof, intended
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>othing elſe but Presbyterie: and as if Presbyterie were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>hing
elſe but the lifting you up into an abſolute, indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent,
uncontroulable Supremacy in all Eccleſiaſticall dignity
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd glory, and by your example are all contrary paties taught
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> plead the <hi>Covenant;</hi> thoſe that you call Sectaries, Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eks,
&amp;c. plead the <hi>Covenant,</hi> engaging each <hi>to go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before other</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> matters of Reformation. The Presbyterian pleads Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nt-engaging
conformity (as they urge) with <hi>the Church of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tland:</hi> The Parliamenteer pleads Covenant, engaging to
<hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſerve the rights and privledges of Parliament:</hi> The Royalliſt
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ads Covenant, engaging to <hi>preſerve and defend the Kings
Majeſties Perſon and Authority:</hi> The Armiſts plead Covenant,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gaging to <hi>preſerve the liberties of the Kingdome,</hi> &amp;c. So that
you have made the Covenant a meere contradictions thing,
like unto one of the Diabolicall Oracles of the Heathens, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng
nothing certaine but ambiguitie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: but let us a little exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
how pertinently you bring i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in in this place, to ſhew the
Parliament and Armie their wickedneſſe, in going about to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring the late King to his Tryall for his vitious, bloody, and
tyrannicall Government; you put them in minde of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn
League and Covenant to <hi>preſerve &amp; defend the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties
Perſon and Authority. in the preſervation and defence of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
Religion and Liberties of the kingdomes, that the world may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
witneſſe with our Conſciences of our loyalty, and that wee have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
thoughts or intentiens to diminiſh his Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſties juſt power and
greatneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, We were bound to <hi>preſerve and defend his Perſon,</hi> when
we firſt took this <hi>Covenant,</hi> and at that time you know very
well you ſtirred up the people to ſight againſt his Army,
though his Perſon was the Leader thereof; which preſume<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:116114:20"/>
firſt, that either you perſwaded the people againſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
of your owne conſciences; or ſecondly, that you conceived
that though his Perſon ſhould be ſmitten into the chambers of
Death by thoſe that did fight againſt his Army, yet they did
not break the Covenant: If ſo, then there is a caſe wherein
the KINGS Perſon may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut off without breach of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The oligation is for the preſervation of his <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
&amp; A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THORITY;</hi> not for his Perſon ſimply, but his
<hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>Authority:</hi> If both come in competition, then the
greater is to be prefer'd before the leſſer; that is, his <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi>
before his <hi>Perſon.</hi> If his Authority (that is, that by which
the execution of all juſt lawes of the Kingdome is legally per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed)
enjoynes the cutting off of Murtherers and Traitors
by death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if his Perſon be found to be a Murtherer or Traitor,
then either his authority or perſon muſt dye. If his Authority
dies, then no Murtherers and Traitors or any other Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents
muſt die or ſuffer; for what reaſon can be given th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the
greateſt Traitor or Murtherer ſhould be ſpared, and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers?
The nearer relations are, the greater is the ſinne of the
violation thereof; the King is the Father, the Husband of his
Countrey, if he ſhall murther his Children, his Spouſe, he
deſerves a ſorer death then common murtherers doe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Treaſon
is the betraying of juſt truſts, the greater the truſt, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
the treaſon, the worſe the Traitor; the Covenant then
engageth to preſerve his Authority rather then his Parſon; for
(though his Perſon may be engaged againſt his people, yet)
his authority cannot withſtand his people, no Prince having
authority to deſtroy, kill, and murther his people; it is
true, he may have <hi>potentiam,</hi> but not <hi>poteſtatem,</hi> an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity,
but not an authority; might, but not right hereunto.
If his perſon riſeth up againſt his authority, and his authority
againſt his perſon; if one of theſe muſt periſh, the Solemne
League and Covenant obligeth us to preſerve his authority,
though with the deſtruction of his perſon.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Covenant binds us to preſerve <hi>his perſon in
the preſervation and defence of the true Religion; true Religion</hi>
doth not command to puniſh the poore, and ſpare the rich;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116114:20"/>
               <hi>true Religion</hi> doth not ſay, if the <hi>Subject</hi> doe kill and murther,
rob and ſteale, he ſhall be ſo and ſo puniſhed: but if the King
doth theſe things a thouſand times over, he muſt not be med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
withall by any but God alone; true Religion ſaith, <hi>he that
ſheds mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed, the murtherer ſhall
ſurely be put to death, the revenger of blood ſhall ſtay the murtherer,</hi>
&amp;c. If then the <hi>King</hi> be a murtherer, <hi>true Religion</hi> comman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
that he <hi>be put to death; true Religion</hi> (as to matter of right or
wrong) maketh no difference, nor hath reſpect of perſone,
it doth not <hi>juſtifie the wicked,</hi> though hee be never ſo great:
and whereas you may urge that the meaning of thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
have a ſpeciall reference to the <hi>Authority</hi> by which the
murtherer muſt be put to death, <hi>by man ſhall his blood be ſhed;</hi>
that is, <hi>by man</hi> inveſted with lawfull authority; not by every
man, or any man; and <hi>that Court by which the King was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
and executed, was no more a lawfull Authority then the
doing thereof by a private perſon, having not the leaſt colour of the
law of the La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d for it.</hi> Saith that profound Lawyer Mr. <hi>Love,</hi>
only <hi>as ſolemn a piece of mockery as ever was acted upon the ſtage of
this world, and ſo thin that every eye may pierce it, and the ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
thereof excepted the ſame with</hi> John <hi>of Leyden.</hi> Saith another
grave and judicious Divine, Mr. <hi>Jenkin; His life being taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
unjuſtly, and his blood drawn by unrighteouſneſſe.</hi> Saith ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
meek Miniſter of the Goſpel, Mr. <hi>Cauton, an imbr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of
their hands with the blood of their Soveraign.</hi> Saith another pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetick
and compaſſionate meſſenger of Jeſus Chriſt, M. <hi>Caſe,
a ſtaining our Land with innocent blood, and notorious ſcand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing
the Proteſtant Religion,</hi> ſay many of the Subſcri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>: but
to anſwer;</p>
            <p>Firſt, This <hi>ſerious and faithfull repreſentation of the judgement
of Miniſters of the Goſpel within the Province of London,</hi> doe not
ſo much as intimate that the life of a King is in any caſe to be
taken away, but rather that the Lords Anointed at no hand
muſt be touched: and the truth is, it is to be feared that this
Doctrine preached by men of this Tribe was one of the great
cauſes both of the Kings wicked and tyranni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll government,
and ſo by conſequence of his death and deſtruction: ſo that if
the King be murthered, the Clergy of this Kingdome have
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116114:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:116114:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:116114:22"/>
murthered him, one part of them being the cauſe of his ſin,
filling and furniſhing him with principles of tyranny, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
party of them ſtirring up the people, and conjuring
them in the name of Chriſt to riſe up againſt him, and to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
him even unto death,<note place="margin">Affirming that men guilty of blood muſt not be at peace with, untill it be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged, <hi>page.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>as <hi>Mr.</hi> Love</hi> in his Sermon at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi>
did. If ſo be that <hi>true religion</hi> which we have Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<hi>to preſerve,</hi> doth teach this Doctrine; theſe Subſcribers in
their <hi>ſerious and faithfull repreſentation of their judgements,</hi> may
doe well to declare it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If ſo be they will grant that Kings and Rulers
are not to be ſuffered to live as they liſt, to murther, kill, and
deſtroy their Subjects, to burne their Houſes, and ruine
their Families at pleaſure, and never be accomptable for the
ſame to their people over whom they were ſet, but ought to
be brought to puniſhment, as many even of the Presbyterian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
and Proteſtant Divines have held, as ſhall be declared; then
(if Kings may be dealt withall in a judiciary way) why are
they ſo angry that the late King was brought to cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gne pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment;
if they ſay they had no authority to judge him, I
demand who had authority to doe it? If they ſay no Court
by the lawes of the Land had any authority hereunto, then
it would be worth our enquiring, whether every man, even
to the laſt man left, was not bound to lay his hands upon him,
for the <hi>murtherer</hi> muſt not be ſuffered to live, but <hi>muſt ſurely be
put to death,</hi> the Land muſt not be defiled and polluted with
blood. If you ſay the Lords and Commons ſhould have done
it, and not the Commons alone, it is demanded, what if the
Lords refuſed to joyne with them, and put them off by an
adjournment of their Houſe, &amp;c. If it be replyed that then the
whole Repreſentative ſhould doe it, and above halfe of them
were violently kept out of the Houſe and detained priſoners,
making themſelves thereby <hi>an unparliamentary Junto,</hi> as Mr.
<hi>Prinne,</hi> called them; it is replyed, that thoſe that were ſo detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
voted a Treaty with the King (after the Houſes when
they were free, had reſolved, voted, and declared upon pai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
of Treaſon, that there ſhould be no further Addreſſe unto
him, nor any Meſſage be carried from him, both Kingdomes
having declared againſt any Treaty with the King untill ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:116114:22"/>
for blood already ſpil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and ſecurity for the peace of
the Kingdome) endeavoured a peace with him, and thereby
to contract the guilt of the blood of the three Kingdomes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the Land, which thoſe that had power and aſſiſtance to
prevent, ought not to ſuffer: that <hi>true religion</hi> which wee had
covenanted to preſerve and defend, requires ſatisfaction for
blood: And this is conſiderable, that the commands of God
to doe Judgement and Juſtice, to put to death the Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,
is given and delivered in the ſame phraſe and manner of
ſpeech a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all the reſt of the commands of God; <hi>Thou ſhalt not
kill, thou ſhalt not ſteale,</hi> &amp;c. So the lawes of puniſhing mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers
were given to <hi>the children of Iſrael,</hi> and not to <hi>Moſes</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
or the Judges and Princes In Iſrael, <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mb.</hi> 35. 10. And
<hi>the Congregation was to judge betweene the ſlayer and the revenger
of blood,</hi> verſ. 24. Whether it was done wittingly, and of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
or by accident; and it is ſaid, verſ. 31. <hi>YEE ſhall take
no ſatisfaction for the life of a Murtherer,</hi> &amp;c. And what is more
common in Scripture then this, that if the King doe popular
wickedneſſe, the people ſuffer, becauſe the King cannot doe
ſuch wickedneſſe but by the people, and the people ought no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
to ſuffer the King ſo to doe: And if the people doe wickedly,
(the King not puniſhing them) the King ſuffers; becauſe did
he execute judgement and juſtice, the people would not doe
wickedly, and God hath not expoſed either the King to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
by the people, or the people by the King, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul
or juſt puniſhment, proportionable unto their mutuall
demerits; and that the people ſhould not ſuffer their Kings &amp;
Rulers to doe wickedly, but ought to puniſh them according
to their demerits, hath been the declared judgement of many
Proteſtant Divinee.</p>
            <p>I ſhall begin with one of theſe Subſcribers, not that I think
he deſerves the honour of priority, but that his own<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> miſtake
may be the more obvious unto obſervation; It is Mr. <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher
Love,</hi> Paſtor of <hi>Anne Alderſgate,</hi> in his Sermon preached
at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge,</hi> and printed, having ſpoken before of the blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiltineſſe
of the King; yea intimated unnaturall and horrible
blood-guiltineſſe in him, as if he had been guilty of K. <hi>James</hi>
his death, and Prince <hi>Henrie's</hi> death, the blood of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:116114:23"/>
in <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hel,</hi> and the Rebellion of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and all the
Proteſtant blood ſhed there, <hi>pag</hi> 23. of the ſaid Sermon, ſtiled
<hi>Englands Diſtemper,</hi> and thereby made him the troubler of
<hi>England,</hi> as <hi>Achan</hi> was of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> hath theſe words, <hi>page</hi> 32.
<hi>It was the Lord that troubled</hi> Achan, <hi>becauſe bee troubled</hi> Iſrael!
<hi>Oh that in this our State, Phyſicians would reſemble God, to cut off
thoſe from the Land who have diſtemperd it. Melius eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> perea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
unus quamunitas.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>—Immedicabile vulnur.</l>
               <l>Enſe recidendum eſt ne pars ſincer a trabatur.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>But yet more plaine, <hi>page</hi> 37. Speaking of thoſe with whom
we ſhould not admit of a peace, hath this intire ſentence—</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Men who he under the guilt of much innocent blood,
are not meet perſons to be at peace with, till all the guilt of blood be
expiated and avenged either by THE SWORD OF THE
LAW, OR LAW OF THE SWORD,</hi> elſe a Peace
can neither <hi>be ſafe nor juſt.</hi> Mr. <hi>Love</hi> will not ſay that the King
was not guilty <hi>of much innocent blood,</hi> leſt he ſhould contradict
himſelfe; neither will he ſay that blood-guiltineſſe can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piated
but by blood, leſt he ſhould contradict the Scriptures:
neither can he ſay, but the King was cut off either <hi>by the ſword
of the Law, OR LAW OF THE SWORD,</hi> without
which he hath already ſaid, that <hi>a Peace can neither be ſafe nor
juſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, Mr. <hi>John Knox,</hi> the Scottiſh Reformer, a man of
known Religion and Learning, of the Presbyterian judgment,
in his 78. page of his Book, called <hi>the appellation of</hi> John Knox,
having declaimed againſt the eſtabliſhment of Idolatrous and
perſecuting Kings and Rulers by the people, hath theſe words,
<hi>Neither can oath or promiſe binde any ſuch people to obey and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
Tyrants againſt God and his truth knowne: but if raſhly they
(viz.</hi> the people) <hi>have promoted any manifeſt wicked perſon, or
yes ignorantly have choſen ſuch an one as after declareth himſelfe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy
of Regiment over the people of God (and ſuch be all Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous
and cruell perſecuters) MOST J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LTLY MAY THE
SAME MEN DEPOSE AND P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NISH HIM, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adviſedly
before they did nominate, appoint, and elect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Againe, Doctor</hi> John Ponnet, a Proteſtant Divine, in his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:116114:23"/>
               <hi>Book<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> called</hi> Aſhore Treatiſe to politique power, <hi>publiſhed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
Queen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Maries <hi>dayes, 1556. in the 45. page, Chap. 6. of the
ſaid Booke, handles this queſtion;</hi> whether it be lawful to depoſe
an evill Governour, and kill a Tyrant: <hi>carri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> it in the affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,
proving the ſame from the very law of Nature, Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
and Scriptures, both Old and New Teſtament; yea,
affirming, that</hi> the lawes of many Chriſtian regions doe permit,
that pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vate men may kill Malefactors; yea, though they were Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates,
in ſome caſes, as when a Governour ſhall ſuddenly with
his ſword runne upon an innocent, or goe about to ſhoot him through
with a gunne; or if he ſhould be found in bed with a mans wife, or
goe about to de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>owr or raviſh a mans daughter; much more if hee
goe about to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ray and make away his Countrey to Forreigners.
<hi>And the ſaid Doctor himſelfe declareth it for his owne opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
that</hi> where execution of juſt puniſhment upon Tyrants,
Idolaters, and trayterous Governours, is either by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he whole State
utterly neglected, or the Prin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with the Nobility and Councell con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire
the ſubverſion of their Countrey and people, any private <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
have ſome ſome ſpeciall inward commandment, or ſurely approved
motion of God, as <hi>Moſes</hi> had to kill the Aegyptian, <hi>Phinea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
lecherous, and <hi>Ahud</hi> King of <hi>Egion,</hi> with ſuch like. <hi>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
affirmes,</hi> If a Prince rob and ſpoile his Subjects it is theft,
a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d as a Thiefe hee ought to be puniſhed: If hee kill and murther
them contrary, or without the lawes of his Countrey, it is mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
and as a murtherer he ought to be puniſht, ſaying the ſame,
if hee commi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> adultery, raviſh men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wives, daughters or maids,
he ought to ſuffer the ſame paines as other the like offenders; if hee
goe about to betray his Countrey, he is a Traitor, and as a Traitor
he ought to ſuffer, <hi>and aboundly more to that purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Junius Brutus,</hi> ſuppoſed by good Authors to be <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za</hi>
his workes, in his Booke called <hi>Vindiciae contra tyrannos,</hi>
written in <hi>Latine</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> and lately tranſlated into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi>
in the 118. page of the ſaid Tranſlation, hath th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe
words; <hi>If the Prince perſiſts in his violent courſes</hi> (as King <hi>Charl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
did) <hi>and contemn frequent a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>onitions, addreſſing his deſign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to
that end, only that he may oppreſſe at his pleaſure, and effect his
owne deſires without reſtraint, hee then doubtleſſe makes himſelfe
liable to that de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſted crime of tyranny: and whatſoever either the</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:116114:24"/>
               <hi>law or lawfull authority permits againſt a Tyrant, may be lawfully
practiſed againſt him. Tyranny is not onely a will, but the chiefe,
and as it were the only abſtract of vices: A Tyrant ſubverts the
State, pillages the people, layes ſtratagems to entrap their lives,
breakes promiſe with all, ſcoffs at the ſacred obligation of a ſolemn
Oath, and therefore hee is ſo much the more vile then the vileſt of
uſuall Malefactors; by how much offences committed againſt a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality,
are worthy of greater puniſhments then thoſe that concerve
only particular and private perſons: If thieves and thoſe that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
ſacriledge be declared infamous; nay if they juſtly ſuffer cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall
puniſhment by death; can we invent any that may be worthily
equivalent for ſo outragious a crime.</hi> And in the 119. page, ſaith
further, if tyranny hath gotten ſuch ſure footing, as there
is no other meanes but force to remove him, then it is lawful
to call the people to arms, &amp;c. Briefely the ſame ſentence
may be juſtly pronounced againſt him as was pronounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<hi>Manlius Capitolinus,</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> Valerius, <hi>lib. 6. cap. 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou waſt to me <hi>Manlius,</hi> when thou diddeſt tumble downe the
Gaules that did ſcale the walls of the Capitoll: but ſince thou art
now become an Enemie like one of them, thou ſhalt be precipitated
downe the ſame place from whence thou formerly tumbledſt thoſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies;
<hi>the ſaid Author hath much more to this purpoſe:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brutus,</hi> Generall of the Souldiers, and <hi>Lucretius</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
of the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> aſſembled the people againſt <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinius
Superbus,</hi> and by their authority thruſt him from his
royall Throne, his goods were confiſcated: and if <hi>Tarquini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>
had been apprehended, undoubtedly he ſhould have been
according to the publique laws corporally puniſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtierne</hi> loſt the Crowne of <hi>Denmarke, Henry,</hi> that of
<hi>Sweden, Mary Steward</hi> (King <hi>Charles</hi> his Grand-mother)
that of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Edward</hi> the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> that of <hi>England,</hi> for
the ſame miſ-government a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our late KING, loſt his Crown
and head.</p>
            <p>That the people may puniſh and correct offending Princes,
is the affirmation of the <hi>Wickeliffs</hi> and <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> and are
therefore enumerated in the catalogue of the <hi>teſtes veritatis,</hi> by
our Foxes Martyrologie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Goodman,</hi> that great aſſociate of <hi>John Knox,</hi> ſaid, that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:116114:24"/>
Queen <hi>Mary</hi> deſerved to be put to death as a Tyrant &amp; m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,
in his Book of obedience, <hi>page</hi> 94.</p>
            <p>That ſuperiour Magiſtrates may be put to death by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour,
becauſe domeſticke Tyrants are chiefly to be repreſt,
was the opinion of <hi>Parreus</hi> in his Commentary on the <hi>Judges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> ought to puniſh that <hi>Mary, Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bel,</hi> whom
they call Queen, ſaid <hi>Knox</hi> that Scottiſh <hi>Luther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That famous <hi>Dudly Fennor</hi> affirms, that an evill Prince may
be taken way, either in a way of juſtice in the time of peace,
or by warre, which they may doe, which are either <hi>ephore or
ordinum omnium conventus,</hi> ſaith he.</p>
            <p>It was <hi>Aſa</hi> his want of zeale, that <hi>Macha</hi> the Queene Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
was not as well put to death as from her regency, <hi>vid.</hi> the
Notes upon the Geneva Bible.</p>
            <p>When a Tyrant is taken away either by the ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge or
conſent of the people; <hi>fit deo auſpice</hi> ſaith <hi>Zwinglius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See more to this purpoſe in a Booke not long ſince put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>,
as it is upon very good grounds ſuppoſed, by Mr. <hi>Rutterford</hi>
of <hi>Scotland,</hi> calleed <hi>Lex Rex:</hi> and eſpecially in Mr. <hi>Pryn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi>
works, chiefly his large 4. volumes of the ſoveraign power of
Parliaments and Kingdomes, where you may read his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
touching capitall proceedings againſt Emperours, Kings
and Princes, for their tyranny, cruelty, &amp;c. eſpecially in his
Appendix to his 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> part of the ſoveraigne power of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
and People, <hi>page</hi> 190, 191, 192, 193. and anſwering
all Objections out of the old Teſtament, and out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
(to which I referre you for the anſwering thoſe very Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts
which you ſo cry up againſt the Parliament and Army) a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alſo
objections from ſuppoſed reaſons, and the example of primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>But becauſe you plead the Covenant againſt the Parliament
and Army, eſpecially the Army, for their irregular c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſe
that they of late have taken, having no authority for wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
they have done: nay all eſtabliſhed authority againſt their
proceedings. If ſo be I can prove that the very like, or a ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
worſe act have been done by others, and yet approved
by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> King <hi>Charles,</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
Parliament, when they were conſiſting both of Lords and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:116114:25"/>
Commons in a full and ample manner; yea and by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery
of <hi>London,</hi> your ſelves, and the Aſſembly of Divines (as
ſuch) that then either you Will for ever hereafter hold your
tongues, or elſe give us ſufficient reaſons of your envaig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
againſt the Army notwithſtanding; for the proof (therefore)
of this, you may pleaſe to beſtow the paines of reading the
Exhortation of the Aſſembly of Divines to the taking of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
Solemn League and Covenant, ordered to be printed by the
Houſe of Commons, <hi>Febr.</hi> 9. 1643. you ſhall find theſe words,
<hi>nor hath this Doctrine or practice (viz.</hi> of entering into a Cov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
without, yea againſt the conſent of the King) <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
ſeditious or unwarrantable by the Princes that have ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e upon
the Engliſh Throne, but juſtified and defended by Queen</hi> Elizabeth,
<hi>of bleſſed memory, with the expence of much treaſure and noble
blood</hi> (obſerve what inſtance is brought) <hi>in the united Provinces
of the Netherlands combined not only without, but againſt the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt
violence of</hi> Philip <hi>of</hi> Spain; <hi>King</hi> James <hi>followed her ſteps, ſo
farre as to approve their union, and to enter into league with them
as free States, which is continued by his Majeſtie now reigning un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
this day</hi> (ſpeaking of King <hi>Charles) who both by his expedition
for the relief<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of</hi> Rochel <hi>in</hi> France, <hi>and his ſtrict confedera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y with
the Prince of Orange &amp; the States Generall, notwithſtanding all the
importunity of</hi> Spain <hi>to the contrary, hath ſet to his Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
hath been done by his Royall Anceſtors in maintenance of thoſe who
had ſo engaged and combined themſelves was juſt and warrantable.</hi>
And what had become of <hi>the Religion, lawes and liberties of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
ſter Nation of</hi> Scotland, <hi>had they not entered into ſuch a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
League and Covenant at the beginning of the late troubles there;
which courſe however it was at firſt by the Popiſh and Frelati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors
repreſented to his Majeſtie as an offence of his, the higheſt
nature, juſtly deſerving chaſtiſement by the fury of a puiſſant Army;
yet when the matters came to be debated firſt by Commisſioners of
both Kingdomes, and then in open Parliament here, it was found
adjudged and declared by the King in Parliament that ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
Brethren of</hi> Scotland <hi>had done nothing but what became loya<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and
obedie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Subjects, and more thereupon by act of Parliament pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely
righted in all the Churches of this Kingdome where they had
been defamed.</hi> To this may be added the late undertakings of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:116114:25"/>
our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> who contrary to the Parliament
and Eſtates, and the eſtabliſhed Law of the Land, did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
any ſhadow, colour, or pretence of warrant from the
State, raiſe Forces under <hi>Arguile</hi> againſt the Forces raiſed
by the authority of Parliament under <hi>Hamil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on;</hi> who were
aſſiſted by the authority of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and
many of the godly Miniſters of <hi>London</hi> did both ſeeke unto
God for their ſucceſſe, and bleſſed the Lord for granting the
ſame. Here are three notorious examples of the ſame actings,
though not with ſo great an Authority as our Armies were; &amp;
why doe you not cry out in your Pulpits againſt the rebellious
<hi>Netherlands,</hi> and the rebellious Scots, as well as the rebellious
Armie, and with what face can you plead the Covenant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the Army for rebellion, which very Covenant was
founded (according to your malignant interpretation ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in your ſence) in rebellion it ſelfe; either anſwer theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,
or for ſhame ſpeake no more of the Covenant.</p>
            <p>By all this it appeares that the Army hath not broken Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
and we were not tyed by the Covenant againſt bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the King to condigne puniſhment, but to defend true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion;
and <hi>true Religion,</hi> and many of the true profeſſors
thereof, would have the perſons of Kings to ſuffer puniſhment
as well as other offendors if they deſerve it: and if ſo; w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
are bound by Covenant to <hi>preſerve the Kings Perſon,</hi> no further
then <hi>in the preſervation of true Religion.</hi> If ſo be the ſaving of
the Kings perſon being a Murtherer, &amp;c. be the deſtruction of
the command of <hi>true Religion,</hi> that <hi>the Murtherer ſhall ſurely be
put to death,</hi> we muſt by the obligation that lies upon us from
the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> cut off the Kings head for <hi>the
preſervation of true Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, We are obliged by the Solemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
to <hi>preſerve and defend the Kings perſon in the preſervation
and liberties of the Kingdomes:</hi> ſo that the Kings <hi>Authority, true
religion, the liberties of the Kingdomes,</hi> are ſtill to be <hi>defended</hi>
and <hi>preſerved</hi> before and above the <hi>Kings perſon:</hi> and the <hi>Kings
perſon</hi> in ſubordination only unto theſe, the <hi>King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> authority &amp;
true religion,</hi> command that if the <hi>Kings perſon</hi> did commit
murther, or was guilty of blood (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe ver, Miniſters at
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:116114:26"/>
leaſt many of them, together with the Miniſters of the Church
of <hi>Scotland</hi> did confeſſe) that his Perſon ſhould be executed;
which neglected, the liberties of the Kingdome could never
be ſecured; for it is righteouſneſſe and juſtice that maketh a
Land to flouriſh, beſides, though theſe Miniſters of Jeſus
Chriſt are pleaſed to ſay, <hi>page</hi> 15. of their <hi>ſerious and faithfull
repreſentation of their judgements,</hi> that <hi>the Parliament</hi> (when the
Army ſeiz'd ſome of the Members thereof) <hi>was acting (viz.</hi>
in the buſineſſe of the Treaty with the King, and their vote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
to ſettle the Kingdome upon his conceſſions) <hi>what was Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted
for, and (if we miſtake not</hi> ſay they) <hi>what was agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
long before by the Parliaments of both Kingdomes,</hi> intimating
thereby as if <hi>the liberties of the Kingdomes</hi> were ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
for and ſecured in the ſaid Treaty; yet there are other
<hi>Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, viz.</hi> The Miniſters of the Church of
<hi>Scotland,</hi> not ſo apt to <hi>miſtake</hi> as our ſubſcribing Miniſters are
in <hi>England,</hi> nor yet ſo apt to be ſeduced and drawne aſide by
Malignants, ſhufling and ſhifting, preaching and printing,
backward and forward, for and againſt, as theſe are, that
concerning the Treaty in the Iſle of Wight, ſpeak <hi>ſeriouſly and
faithfully</hi> in their late <hi>neceſſary and ſeaſonable teſtimony againſt tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration</hi>
in page 12. after this manner; <hi>And doubtleſſe the Lord
is highly diſpleaſed with their proceedings in the Treaty at Newport,
in reference to Religion and Covenan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, concerning which they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted
of ſuch concesſions from his Majeſtie as being acquieſced in,
were dangerous and deſtructive to both.</hi> It ſeemes theſe Miniſters
of Jeſus Chriſt in London, I meane theſe Subſcribers, could
<hi>acquieſce in ſuch conceſſions</hi> from the King; which being <hi>acquieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
in,</hi> the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt in <hi>Scotland</hi> doe profeſſe
were <hi>dangerous and deſtructive</hi> both to Religion and Covenant.
Here are Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt of the Province of <hi>London,</hi>
and Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> both
pretending an Embaſſie from the ſame Lord, and yet as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
one to the other as ſalvation is to deſtruction; ſurely
contradiction<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cannot be truth, the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt
in <hi>London</hi> plead Covenant for the Parliaments acquieſcing in
the conceſſions of the King at <hi>Newport,</hi> which (by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
of the whole Miniſtery of <hi>Scotland</hi>) acquieſced in, would
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:116114:26"/>
deſtroy both Religion and Covenant; if the keeping the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
deſtroye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Covenant in Miniſters of <hi>London<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
the breaking of Covenan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preſerves the Covenant in the
Miniſters of <hi>Scotlands</hi> judgement: I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not this the way to make
the Covenant like <hi>AN ALMANACKE O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TO<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
DATE?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeemes our Miniſters (the Subſcribers) make little diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
betweene Covenant or no Covenant, Religion or no
Religion, when theſe ſtand in their way; but are ready to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce
in that which deſtroyes both the one and the other;
whether Biſhops be aboliſhed, or not aboliſhed, whether ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants
be puniſhed, or not puniſhed: Nay, they can plead
for the King, or joyne with Malignants, or what not, in the
proſecution of their game, though the Miniſter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Scotland</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
of another opinion.</p>
            <p>Theſe Subſcribers make little difference between ſeven men
excepted from pardon in the late Treaty at <hi>Newpor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
of theſe out of the reach of Juſtice; an olde man, Judge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>,
that never perſonally ſhed blood, only left behind, and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bout 37. or 38. before excepted from mercie by the 2. King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omes,
<hi>the liberties of the Kingdomes,</hi> Religion, Covenant, all
muſt velle and pay tribute unto theſe men.</p>
            <p>In the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> place whereas th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe Miniſters both in <hi>their ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
and faithfull repreſentation of their judgements;</hi> and in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
vindication plead <hi>Covenant:</hi> I deſire to know of them whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
one of the great and capitall ends both of the Covenant
and Warre it ſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e; hath not expreſly beene ſet forth by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
Kingdoms from time to time to be the bringing of Delinquents
<hi>to condign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> puniſhment,</hi> and is made the ſubject matter of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Article thereof; is not this then an abhominable mocker<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
in the fight of Heaven and Earth? and ſhall this be indulged
and pleaded for by <hi>the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt in the Province
of London?</hi> Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you thinke the blood of ſo many thouſand
Proteſtants in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> could be expla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d by the
blood of <hi>David <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> who was not ſo much guilty of blood
in all theſe War<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome of your ſelves have been in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
men up to the late ſecond War<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e? Is this your keeping of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant?
Is this the fruit of all your Sermons, laſting and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:116114:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:116114:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:116114:28"/>
exciting and ſtirring up the Parliament as ſeverall of
your printed Sermons doe witneſſe, <hi>to cauſe judgement and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> downe like amighty flood amongſt u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>?</hi> Will the blood
of <hi>David Jenkin</hi> make ſuch a flood think you? You ſay to the
Army, page 12. <hi>be not deceived, God is not mocked:</hi> but they
may retort it upon your ſelves, and God will require the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
things at your hands above all others.</p>
            <p>In the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and laſt place, whereas you alwayes plead <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn
League and Covenant</hi> (and leaving the Scriptures) cry o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Covenant, Oath of God, Covenant of the Lord,</hi> and <hi>breach of
Covenant, perjury,</hi> &amp;c. Doth not the All-ſeeing eye of Heaven
know, and will he not judge think you betweene you and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
in theſe things: hath any generation, party, or ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of men in the Kingdome taken more Oaths, Vowes, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants,
directly croſſe and contrary each to other then your
ſelves? Looke backe into your former courſe of life, and call
to minde how many oaths and ſubſcriptions, ſubſcription<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
and oaths you have made from time to time, over and over,
and how you have either made it a meere, vaine, ſinfull, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary
thing, to ſwear ſolemnly in the ſight of Heaven and
Earth, or have been very raſh, haſty, and injudicious. In ſo
doing, or 3<hi rend="sup">dly</hi> have directly forſworn your ſelves againſt the
light and ſence of your own judgement and conſcience; have
we not cauſe to judge better of many of the Prelaticall party,
who being men of learning and conſcience, and never ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
againſt their oppoſers in Church and State as your ſelves
making no diſturbances, rents, diviſions, factions by Pul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
and Preſſe as you doe from day to day (as all men obſerve)
that being conſcious to themſelves of the many Oaths, Vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
Covenants that they have made of ſubjection and obedien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
unto Biſhops, the then eſtabliſhed Church-government <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
of Common-prayer, Homilies, Canons, &amp;c. cannot take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
Solemn League and Covenant, and rather chooſe to loſe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
livings and livelihoods, committing themſelves, Wives and
Children to the mercy of God, having no viſible meanes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
ſubſiſting, then to break the peace of their conſciences by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
an Oath, Vow, and Covenant, contrary to all their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
oaths before ſatisfaction received; then for you or ſome of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:116114:28"/>
you that preſently turn'd Presbyterian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, caſt away Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy,
tooke the Covenant: and having taken it, turne in
and wind it, wring it and wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt it, making it to looke Eaſt
and Weſt, North and South, as your intereſt works with
King, Parliament, or Army, or againſt them all: and this
is not my ſaying only, whom I expect you will repreſent
as a Schiſmatick, Sectary, Hereticke, a bold, impudent,
inconſiderate, &amp;c. But it is <hi>Vox Populi,</hi> the late KING,
the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the Commons, the City, the Countrey, the
whole Kingdome obſerved it; it would have been rather expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
that you ſhould have made, publiſhed, and printed a
Recantation of all your former Oaths, Vows, Covenants,
Promiſes, Subſcriptions; then (as if people knew neither you
nor your wayes) to exclaime at men for breaking Cove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>,
becauſe they ſubject not themſelves unto your intereſt and
judgement under the Notion of Presbytery, putting th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
Crown upon Chriſts head, building his houſe, &amp;c. not one
word of Presbytery in the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and the very mention of
Epiſcopacy and Government of the Church by the Arch-Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ops,
Biſhops, &amp;c. expreſly made in ſome of your former <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
which you have taken; you tell the Army, <hi>page</hi> 9. of your <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
and faithfull repreſentation,</hi> that they have <hi>made Religion
to ſtinke by reaſon of their miſcarriages, and like to become a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
and reproach in all the Chriſtian world.</hi> The truth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, they have
ſpread the ſweete ſavour of Religion abroad throughout this
Kingdome more then thouſands of thoſe that ſtile themſelves
the Miniſters of the Goſpell, and Embaſſadors of Jeſus Chriſt.
And although ſome of them may have ſome miſtaken about
religion in ſome points thereof, as you cannot deny <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
your ſelves have their errors; yet their fame in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
hath ſounded throughout all the Chriſtian world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
all Armies that ever were before them; notwithſtanding
all your blacke lines and language, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owle, ſcandalous, and
falſe aſperſions caſt upon them and this Kingdome in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall
parts of it, yea in almoſt all the parts of it, yea and the
Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> alſo have received full and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ple teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
of their worthineſſe, and declared the ſame to your
vexation unto all the world, and whether that your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:116114:29"/>
have not made <hi>Religion to ſtinke</hi> (I would not uſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
words were they not your owne) <hi>and like to become a ſcorne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
reproach to all the Chriſtian world:</hi> Let all men judge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nay, the
truth is, almoſt all men have already given in their judgment
againſt you, many of your own party being more moderate,
meek, and conſiderate then your ſelves, have declin'd you, and
are aſham'd of you; no men, party, or faction, Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,
Hereticks, or call you them what you pleaſe, have
been greater hinderers of Reformation, or the eſtabliſhment
of a moderate, holy, peaceable, quiet advancement of the
Kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt and his truth and Goſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll, be it
Presbytery or whatſoever elſe then your ſelves have been, and
you may thus contend all your dayes: but you will never
thrive and proſper in the ſettlement of Religion and Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
untill a more meeke, quiet, forbearing ſpirit be more
predominant in you then as yet doth appear; which if it once
be made manifeſt in you, your parts, gifts, and abilities would
be ſerviceable unto God, and your faces would ſhine in the
ſight of honeſt men.</p>
            <p>Having repeated the Proteſtation, Vow and Covenant, and
Solemn League and Covenant, as if your very calling men
Covenant-breakers had ſufficiently proved them ſo, you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
flye into the faces of the Army with all thoſe Scriptures
that make mention of Gods diſpleaſure againſt Covenant-breaking,
and that without once giving any argument, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
that they are Couenant-breakers: but what have been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered
over and over, again and again, though you have
gotten the art not to take notice thereof; then you tell them
<hi>page</hi> 8. of your <hi>ſerious and faithfull repreſentation,</hi> with what
<hi>a jealous eye and ſevere hand the Lord avenged the quarrell, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
Covenant made by</hi> Zedekiah <hi>King of Babylon;</hi> then wee heare of
God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>avenging the quarrell of his Covenant,</hi> of <hi>deſpiſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
Oath, by breaking his Covenant,</hi> of <hi>lifting up the hand to the
high God; of the deſpiſing Dominions, and ſpeaking evill of Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities;
of Gods judgements againſt</hi> Corah, Dathan, <hi>and</hi> Ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram
<hi>for their mutinous rebellion and levelling deſign againſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y
and Miniſtery in the perſons of</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Aaron, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.
But may not others upon better grounds ſummon up all thoſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:116114:29"/>
Scriptures that ſpeake of the miſcarriages of falſe Prophet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>,
that prophecie lies in the name of the Lord; that pretend to
a viſion from God which hee did never ſhew, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
meſſages which he did never ſend, &amp;c. and daſh them all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
your faces, then you can thoſe Scriptures that ſpeak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of
Covenant-breaking, deſpiſing Magiſtracy and Miniſtery,
into the faces of the Army; you tell them of Gods judgments
againſt <hi>Saul</hi> for violating the Covenant which was made
with the <hi>Gibe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nites:</hi> but may not that as well be re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
you for violating the Covenant which you made with the
Parliament, <hi>not to make defection to the contrary party, to aſſiſt
the Forces raiſed and continued by authority of Parliament, to
bring Delinquents to condign puniſhment,</hi> &amp;c. which is a poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,
not conditionall Article of the Covenant (as that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
the preſervation of the perſon of the King was) yea one of
the great ends of the whole warre, and when the Lord Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
and Councell of Waried <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>once yeeld unto Articles of
quarter for life (upon very weighty grounds and reaſons ſo
voted by the Parliament themſelves) to ſome capitall Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ant
at the rend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion of <hi>Oxford;</hi> what a clamour and noiſe was
heard againſt them, though we hear as great an exclamation
for their contrary proceedings at this time.</p>
            <p>Againe, Did the Covenant made with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Gibeonites</hi> give
them a diſpenſation to doe what they could againſt the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites,</hi>
and they muſt not ſo much as be queſtioned for it by
vertue of a Covenant made before: If not, your inſtance is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
for no ſuch Covenant was made with the King, that
doe he what he would or could to ruine and deſtroy religion
and liberty, and all godly men, that yet we bound our ſelves
to preſerve his Perſon: and you know that when wee entered
into this Covenant, it was p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſumed that not the King, but
his evill councell was the cauſe of our Warres and miſeri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>,
though ſince wee have found that not his councell, but
himſelfe was the chiefe cauſe thereof, and your own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
do tell you ſo, or elſe you have wrong'd him.</p>
            <p>Page 9. of your Letter, you tell them while they kept <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi>
they had <hi>your hearts, your helpe, and your prayers;</hi>
that they have broken their <hi>Covenant,</hi> is your ſlanderous aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſion,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:116114:30"/>
and how <hi>your hearts, your help, and your prayers</hi> have
been towards them, is all mens obſervation; that the very
ſcope and drift of many of your prayers and preaching, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially
the laſt Summer, and about 18. months ſince, was
to rend and teare the Army to pieces, and like <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m's</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
for the hoſts of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (though bleſſed be God with the like
ſucceſſe) may be proved by many heaps of witneſſes, and yet
the Armies ſucceſſe in all their proceedings muſt ſtill be appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated
to your prayers that were bent againſt them, though
indeed in ſome ſence it cannot be denyed; for it is uſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I with
God to turne mens curſes againſt his people into bleſſing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
their head<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Having ſufficiently inſiſted upon the <hi>Solemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi>
by way of anticipation, you anſwer their objection by
telling them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, That they</hi> muſt not be too confident from former ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
ſhewing them that God ſuffers men ſometimes to proſper in
wicked courſes; that there be juſt men unto whom it happens accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the worke of the wicked, and that there be wicked men unto
whom it happeneth according to the worke of the righteous. <hi>Page</hi>
12. <hi>of your Letter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to reply in the firſt place, why may not they conclude
from ſucceſſes as well as you, how often have we heard you
attribute the ſucceſſes of the Army from time to time, to your
prayers and morning meetings and Lectures, though made
uſe of both by prayer and preaching, to render them odi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
in the ſight of God and man (if it was poſſible) but</p>
            <p>2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. Though ſucceſſes are not alwayes the infallible teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies
of the goodneſſe of the cauſe on which ſide they fall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
yet ſucceſſes with their circumſtances doe ſometimes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
evidently vindicate the minde of God in a queſtionable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
as,</p>
            <p>Firſt, when both parties have appealed ſolemnly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
God in a doubtfull caſe, or at leaſt ſo appearing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
him to bleſſe or blaſt, make to proſper or to periſh that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
that is not righteous in his eyes: As for inſtance, when the
falſe Prophets commanded to goe up to <hi>Ramoth Giliad,</hi> and
proſper: and the Prophet of the Lord told them that if they
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:116114:30"/>
went up they ſhould periſh, and both parties pretended to
the meſſage of the Lord herein. Certainly the ſucce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe in
this caſe argueth the minde and will of God, touching th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
going or not going to <hi>Ramo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h Giliad,</hi> when ſome of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> did
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id the City goe out againſt the Army, when they came to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
the City, telling them you had a command from God
to this purpoſe, aſſuring them that if they did let the Army
come in,<note place="margin">1646.</note> they would plunder the City, ruine and deſtroy
them. And others of the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ending
to the ſame name and authority a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you did, required
them in the name of the Lord not to goe out to fight againſt
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Army, aſſuring that if the Army did come, not a hai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir heads ſhould periſh. Doubtleſſe the ſucceſſe in this caſe
was very argumentative touching the will of God: So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
the <hi>Scots</hi> came the laſt yeare into this Kingdome, pretending
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he quarrell of the Covenant (for whoſe proſperity ſome of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id ſo earneſtly pray unto God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your Pulpits) and ſome part
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Army of <hi>England</hi> though under many diſadvantages,
was about to engage againſt them, prayer being ſolemnly
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade unto God by the Commander in Chiefe<note n="*" place="margin">I. Gen. Cromwell.</note>, impor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ing
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od, that for as much as both parties did pretend unto the
Covenant, that they did refer themſelves unto the Lord, and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>egg'd from heaven to give ſentence between them. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe
either ſuch pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yers are vaine, or God doth uſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd to inform us of his mind by anſwering herein: ſo here,
when you have endeavoured to curſe the Army from Pariſh
to Pariſh, and from Pulpit to Pulpit, to ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re up the City
and Countrey, to joyne with Malignants and Royalliſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the Army, aſſuring your party that God will breake
them and rend them. And another party of Miniſters pray
for them from Pulpit to Pulpit, from place to place, encon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing
them not to feare, for God will be with them: d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ht<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
the ſucceſſe is very declara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve touching the will of God
herein, and eſpecially,</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, when thoſe ſucceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are carryed on
from time to time in an uniform manner, the Lord giving
ſeverall years ſucceſſe upon their ſeverall appeal unto him:
and yet more,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:116114:31"/>
In the third place, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the glorious Majeſty, power and
preſence of God doth appeare after ſuch appeales made unto
God, when the Lord doth (as it were) ſend the Ang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll of
his preſence to ſave his people, being few, and the Angel
of his fury to make the Armies, the great and mighty hoſts of
the Enemie to flie and ſcatter as duſt before the face of the
winde, when hee makes one to chaſeten, and two to put a
hundred to flight; <hi>when he breakes the heavens and comes down,
making the mountaines to flow downe at his preſence;</hi> when hee
ſhall with alſmal inconſiderable Army of about 16000 men,
ſcattered and divided in ſeverall diſperſions. <hi>Eaſt, Weſt;
North and South,</hi> to deſtroy neare a hundred thouſand men
in armes (as if the <hi>Scots</hi> Army, the <hi>Welch</hi> Army, the <hi>Kent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi>
Army, the <hi>Eſſex</hi> Army were conſidered, it would appear
beſides the City and Ships all engaged,) yea and ſhould take
away the hearts and ſpirits of their Enemies, and make the
proud, high, and lofty thoughts of their adverſaries to trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.
Certainly ſuch kinde of ſucceſſes, wherein God doth
appear in the very majeſty of his power and preſence, cannot
but be very convincing, touching the truth of their cauſe: and
you above all others, who ſhould rather exhort Malignants,
Royalliſts, and the enemies of the peace and liberties of the
Kingdome in generall, and the people of God in ſpeciall to
give glory to God, to cauſe the high praiſes of God to be in
their l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ps, <hi>who hath pul'd downe the mighty from their ſeate, and
raiſed up the poore out of the duſt, that he may ſet him with Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ces,
even the Princes of his people: That the loftineſſe of man is
bowed downe, and the haughtineſſe of men is bowed downe, and
the Lord alone is exalted in the worke.</hi> I appeale unto all your
conſciences, whether God did ever appear ſince the comming
of Chriſt in more viſible characters &amp; prints of his foot ſteps,
then in bringing downe that proud <hi>Nimrod,</hi> and in executing
vengea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce upon that hardned <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> who did yet more
and more harden his heart againſt all the wonderful appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances
of God againſt him, and would not bow and bend, and
ſubject himſelfe unto the God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Nay I appeal yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
you, whether the millions of prayers and teares that have
been powred forth u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>to God by his faithfull ſervants in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:116114:31"/>
and in private, in Churches and in chambers, did not
beget a faithfull expectation that God would make him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary
in mercy or judgement, returning thoſe prayers ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
upon his heart or head. And I appeale likewiſe unto
you, whether he hath not anſwered ſuch expectations accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly,
cauſing him at ſuch a time, in ſuch a manner, to be
brought to cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gn puniſhment, as was beyond all the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations
either of his friends or enemies, the like n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver
known in our Nation. And I appeal further unto you, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
you doe not think in your conſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ences (or have not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
reaſon ſo to doe) that if ever he had come unto his
Throne again, he would not have made as great havocke of
godly men, whether <hi>Presbyteria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Independent,</hi> or what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
elſe, as <hi>Nero</hi> himſelfe hath done; and whether you would
not have been driven into your old corners, chamber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and
cloſets, and there teare him to pieces with your prayers; is it
not then to be lamented, that you ſhou'd (you above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers)
caſt a blinde before mens eyes, and hide the glorious
preſence and appearances of God, evidenced by thoſe great
and moſt ſtupendious ſucceſſes vouchſafed unto the Army in
bringing that man of blood unto judgement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The next thing you anticipate the Army, is, that they pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
not their juſtification of their preſent actings from</hi> impulſes of
ſpirit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orpretended impreſſions on their hearts, without or againſt
the rule of Gods written word. <hi>Page 13. of your Letter,</hi> putting
them to conſider, whether any hiſtory, ſacred or profane, recordeth
any example of an impulſe of ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rit falling upon multitudes of p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
at the ſame time, putting them all at once upon perform<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nces
contrary to morall precepts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be demanded of you who call your ſelves the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
of God, and Embaſſadors of Jeſus Chriſt, and who
wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d be looked upon as guided by the Spirit of God, and
ſpeaking in your Pulpits as he gives you utterance; <hi>whether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
hiſtory, ſacred or profane, recordeth any example</hi> of the true
ſpirit of God falling upon a great company of the faithfull.
Embaſſadours and true Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>putting
them all at once upon performances contrary to morall precepts and</hi>
principles, making them violate the rules of civility and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:116114:32"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:116114:32"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:116114:33"/>
ſpeake and write moſt notorious, ſcandalous, and
known falſities, when another part of the Miniſters of Jeſus
Chriſt doe ſpeak and write directly contrary unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he former.
This ſpirit that hath made you abuſe the Army, by caſting
filthy reproaches upon them and the Parliament, by ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalizing
the higheſt act of Juſtice that ever was performed in
this Land, calling it ſedition, rebellion, murther, ſtaining
the Land with the blood of their Soveraign, I believe came
not <hi>from above,</hi> neither had it any higher aſcent then the aire,
or an upper roome in <hi>Sion-Colledge,</hi> from whence the City,
and Countrey-Miniſters capable of the impreſſion, receive
<hi>an impulſe of ſpirit,</hi> to ſpeake and write (as it were) with one
month and penne, <hi>as that ſpirit</hi> of errour and ſcandall <hi>gives
them utterance;</hi> that the holy ſpirit of God makes no impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s
upon the hearts of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>without and againſt the word
of God, putting them upon performances contrary to morall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepes,</hi>
cannot be denyed: but that there are ſuch pretences
either in the Army to whom you write, or the Parliament,
or high Court of Juſtice, who are alike concern'nd in what
you ſay for doing ſuch things, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but the inſpiration of that
ſpirit in you which ſtands in perfect contradiction to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
of God: and theſe <hi>impulſes of ſpirit, and impreſſions upon the
hearts</hi> of the Army, to put the Parliament into a condition
and capacity of executing judgement and juſtice upon that
great Delinquent of the Land, and which did inſpire the
higheſt Court of Juſtice with courage and faithfulneſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
was the ſame ſpirit whole finger hath written that <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
precept in the hearts of men,</hi> and that ſacred <hi>rule of Gods
written word,</hi> Numb. 35. 16. <hi>The murtherer ſhall ſurely be put
to deaih.</hi> And verſ. 31: <hi>Yee ſhall take no ſatisfaction for the life
of a murtherer:</hi> and all thoſe other Scriptures, commanding to
execute judgement and juſtice impartially; and that ſpirit
that would not have the K. (guilty by your owne confeſſions
of the blood of many thouſands) ſo much as <hi>convict &amp; condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi>
(as you declared your ſelves, <hi>page</hi> the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of your Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation)
much leſſe executed, notwithſtanding ſuch blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiltineſſe,
can be no other then that ſpirit which ſaid unto
our firſt Parents, contrary to the expreſſe word of God, <hi>Gen.</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:116114:33"/>
3. 4. <hi>Yee ſhall not ſurely dye.</hi> Morall principles, and the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
Word of God ſaith, that the blood guilty perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n muſt
dye, you ſay that the greateſt blood-guilty peſon in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
ſhall not ſurely dye: <hi>that impulſe of ſpirit, and thoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions
of heart</hi> that were in the Subjects of <hi>Amaziah</hi> King
of <hi>Judah,</hi> putting him to death for his wickedneſſe, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi>
25. 27. (The word of God not blaming them for any thing
we hear of) and that ſtirred up <hi>Jehoiadab</hi> the Prieſt to raiſe
up ſeverall parties to put Queene <hi>Athaliah</hi> to death for her
cruelty and murthers; did ſtir up the Army, Parliament, and
Court of Juſtice to put the late bloody Tyrant to death, and
we may expect (through the grace of God) reſt and peace as
the iſſue thereof; for it is a bleſſing to a Kingdome to doe ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
impartially, and a curſe to neglect it, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2. 32, 33.
<hi>Numb. 35. 33, 34. Jer.</hi> 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 5, 6. and ſince you ſpeake of
<hi>impulſe of ſpirit, and impreſſions of heart, without and againſt
the rule of Gods written word, putting men upon performances
contrary to worall precepts.</hi> It would be known in what <hi>heart</hi>
was this <hi>written</hi> as a <hi>morall</hi> principle, that Kings and Princes
though they ſhould prove Tyrants, murtherers, Traytors,
&amp;c. yet it is a ſinne to put them to death. In what booke or
page of the holy Bible is the execution of ſuch perſons ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted
from juſtice; you ſay <hi>to the law and to the teſtimonis, if
they ſpeak not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light
in them.</hi> Surely if you cannot produce ſuch a <hi>law and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi>
inhibiting the execution of juſtice upon perſons of Kings
and Princes, guilty of murther, treaſon, &amp;c. You have
taught us by Scripture to conclude againſt you, that <hi>there is
no light in you</hi> as concerning your opinion in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s caſe: but
that you are ſteered by an <hi>impulſe of ſpirit &amp; impreſſions of heart</hi>
againſt the expreſſe word and will of God.</p>
            <p>In the third place you anticipate the Armies plea of <hi>neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi>
urging that of <hi>Job:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 13. 7.</note> 
               <hi>will yee ſpeake wickedly for God, and
talke deceitfully for him,</hi> that <hi>no neceſſity can juſtifie perjurie, or
diſpenſe with lawfull oaths,</hi> page 14, 15. of your Letter.</p>
            <p>I may reply by re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orting your owne argument, where
you ſay,<note place="margin">Page 15. of your Letter.</note> that <hi>if a precept of God may be diſpenſed with upon a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity,
yet this neceſſity muſt be abſolute, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd cleare,</hi> that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:116114:34"/>
               <hi>the murtherer ſhall ſurely be put to death,</hi> is a knowne <hi>precept of
God:</hi> If th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt be diſpenſed withall, ſhew us <hi>the abſolute,
preſent, and cleare neceſſity for it.</hi> If you cannot, <hi>will you ſpeake
wickedl, for God, and talke deceitfully for him?</hi> As for the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
proceedings, if there was a <hi>neceſſity</hi> that the land ſhould
be c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eanſed from blood guiltineſſe, that the great ends of the
Covenant and all our Wars ſhould be ſecured, <hi>viz.</hi> the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Delinquents to cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gn puniſhment, <hi>the reformation of
Religion according to the word of God, and the example of the beſt
r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmed-Churches,</hi> the eſtabliſhment of righteouſneſſe and
juſtice in the middeſt of us, then was there a <hi>necesſity</hi> of the
Army to take that courſe which they did.</p>
            <p>You conclude your Letter with your ſerious exhortat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on
to the Army to decline their preſent actings, and declaring
unto them your M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niſterial faith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſſe in dealing p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ainly
with them, expecting ſufferings, and telling your Readers
a ſtory of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Peters</hi> language, ſtrengthning your expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of a ſuffering condition, <hi>page</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>Had the Army alwayes obeyed the law of your lips, it had
been no hard matter to prophecy what had become of us by
this time: Doubtleſſe <hi>Rome</hi> had been the pattern of the Ecleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical
Reformation, and <hi>Turkey</hi> of the civil liberties of this
Kingdome before now, had religious <hi>Masſie,</hi> and devout
<hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iniz,</hi> and thoſe piou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Reformades, your Champions of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſtirred up to ſight againſt the Army, that did cut, flaſh
and kill the Citizens in the <hi>Guild Hall,</hi> London, prevailed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the Army; doe not you think we ſhould have had moſt
pious and prec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous times by this? As for Mr. <hi>Peters,</hi> whoſe
bloody language you ſo <hi>ſeriouſly and faithfully</hi> repreſent in
your <hi>ſerious and faithfull repreſentation:</hi> Let the Readers under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
the truth of the matter, which (your own conſciences
can witneſſe) was thus: Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> and ſome others were ſent
to you from the Councel of Warre (whom you had offended
by your invectives, ſlanders and ſcandals in prayer and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings
without your comming unto them, to give or receive
ſatisfaction touching their proceedings) who in the name of
thoſe that ſent them certified from whence they came, and
for what end; Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> told you that they came in obedience
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:116114:34"/>
to Chriſts rule in <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. telling you that you had offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
your Brethren of the Army by your Pulpit exclamations
againſt them, deſiring that if you had any thing to ſay tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
any of their actings, you would come unto them, and
they would give or receive ſatisfaction, repeating this unto
you over and over to prevent miſtakes; adding moreover, that
they did not come to ſcare you, neither were affraid of
you; what proud, Prelaticall, imperious, and unbrotherly
language he received from ſome of you, is very well knowne,
though hee had a more civill and candid reception from ſome
others; the diſcourſe which was had with him was intended it
ſeemes on your part, to catch matter of an ill reſentment to
publiſh it againſt him, one of you pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſing the dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences
of proceeding againſt the King, likely engaging into
more warr, occaſioned Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> to ſay that the Army did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve
to <hi>give no man quarter in the next Warre,</hi> (or to that purp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſe,
which words you repreſent as threatning you) to which
reply was given, that you did expect ſufferings, &amp;c. To this
Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> ſaid, that if you <hi>put your ſelves upon ſuffering, you
may have ſuffering enough,</hi> or to that purpoſe, and adviſed
you moreover to forbeare your provoking language in your
Pulpits, leſt the <hi>common ſouldiers ſhould doe you a miſchieſe, and
you may thanke your ſelves.</hi> This was the ſum of that diſcourſe,
and now let any man judge whether he did you any wrong in
all this, or where lies the unbrotherlineſſe and unworthineſſe
of theſe paſſages; or whether your <hi>Chriſti in ingenuity and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor
becomming the Miniſters of the Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> doth
not gloriouſly appear in printing Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> unto the world at
you have done.</p>
            <p>And now let heaven and earth judg whether that the whole
<hi>ſeries</hi> of your former proceedings doe not <hi>ſpeake plainely, and
not in parables,</hi> that as the Popes of old did command men to
ſubject unto Magiſtracy as <hi>Gods Ordinance,</hi> and unto <hi>Kings</hi>
and Rulers, as unto thoſe that <hi>were ſet over them</hi> by the Lord
<hi>for their good,</hi> while theſe Kings and Rulers did ſubject <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
unto them, caſting downe their Crownes at their feet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then they ſhall have titles of honour confer'd upon them,
as <hi>Moſt Chriſtian King, Catholique King, Defender of the Faith,</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:116114:35"/>
&amp;c. and to allure them to permit that <hi>Romiſh</hi> Harlot <hi>to reigne
over the Kings of the earth,</hi> Revel. 17. 18. that <hi>ſhee might fit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
Queene.</hi> Shee would chant them with her alluring tongue;
<hi>her lips dropping as an honey-comb,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 5. 4.</note> 
               <hi>and her mouth ſmoother then eyl,</hi>
and bewitching them with her guilded language, during their
obedience to the holy chaire, they ſhould be called <hi>the frinds of
Jeſus Chriſt, ſonnes to St.</hi> Peter, <hi>obedient children to their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Church:</hi> aſſuring them <hi>that God would be mercifull unto them
when he came with</hi> St. Peter <hi>to judge the world,</hi> they ſhould have
Indulgences and pardons for all their ſinnes, they ſhould have
their Holineſſes benedictions, and the prayers of the Church
to proſper them in their wars &amp; expeditions for their ſucceſſe
in the advance of the Catholique cauſe; yea for a time, untill
their turns be ſerved, they ſhall have an acknowledgment that
ſuch and ſuch things are proper unto them, which afterward
it ſhall be no leſſe then ſacriledg to proclaim, <hi>viz.</hi> The calling
of generall Councels, appointing and ordering the elections
of Popes, and the inveſtitures of Biſhops; yea ſometimes to
court Princes, ſpared not to preſent them with the treaſures of
the Church, as Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> did <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> when he
ſent him the keyes of the holy Sepulchre, and S. <hi>Peters</hi> chains,
and other things; all which, at other times, when they were
ſixt in their chair of peſtilence, they ſtifly affirmed to be irrela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
to them: and for claiming of which, pronounced them
guilty of Simony, and excommunicated them. And when at
any time theſe threw off the papall yoke, the very ſame Popes
did iſſue out their Buls againſt them, and did abſolve the
people from any further ſubjection unto them, even ſo doe
not you (I ſtill ſpeake not of all, but ſome of you) when that
authority ſtears by your compaſſe, then all goes right; then
<hi>we bleſſe you in the name of the Lord;</hi> then you can <hi>bid them God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeed;</hi>
then <hi>they ſhall be called the repairers of Iſrael,</hi> and of the
<hi>breaches of Zion,</hi> and <hi>ages to come ſhall call them bleſſed;</hi> then <hi>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
on and proſper;</hi> then they are the <hi>Zerubbabels,</hi> the <hi>Davids,</hi> the
<hi>Solomons,</hi> the <hi>Worthies of Iſrael;</hi> theſe are the bleſſed times of
Reformation: If any in place of authority doe withſtand and
oppoſe, though it be the King himſelfe, and ſeverall of the
Rulers with him, as the late King and many Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:116114:35"/>
did, then how did you allarm the people, conjuring
them in the name of the Lord to <hi>goe out againſt them to fight the
Lords battles;</hi> then <hi>curſe yee Meroz, curſe yee bitterly the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants
thereof, becauſe they went not out to help the Lord againſt the
mighty.</hi> And as for thoſe Magiſtrates or others, that drive on
in a hopefull advance of your intereſt, then <hi>my heart is towards
the Governours of Iſrael that gave themſelves willingly,</hi> &amp;c. And to
encourage the people, you tell them that Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
and all authority and power muſt ſtoop unto Jeſus Chriſt
and <hi>he will break<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them in pieces like a potters veſſell:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Your ſeverall Sermons in print will wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe this.</note> 
               <hi>He will bind
their Kings in chaines, and their Nobles in fetters of iron: And
this honour ſhall all the Saints have.</hi> Then goe out and <hi>feare not
the battle is the Lords, and he will teach your hands to warre, and
your fingers to fight, and cover your heads in the day of battle.</hi> Then
you tell them, if they be not <hi>valiant, and quit themſelves like
men, their eares ſhall be boared,</hi> and themſelves, their wives and
children ſhall be everlaſting ſlaves and vaſſals; then their eyes
ſhall be put out as were <hi>Sampſons,</hi> and they muſt be the ſport
and ſcorn of their enemies, and grind in their mills all their
dayes; then you cry, how will your children, and your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens
children curſe your cowardize, and bewaile your trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous
betraying their peace and liberties, therefore you ſtir
up the people to aſſiſt with moneyes, horſe, plate, and perſons
If any doubts doe ariſe concerning reſiſting Kings and Rulers,
eſpecially in caſe of Oaths, Vows, or Covenants, touching
preſervation of the perſon of the King (as there did from the
Solemn League and Covenat) then you are ready to give ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction,
and to tell the people that that clauſe in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
is to be underſtood not <hi>ſimply,</hi> but <hi>relatively;</hi> that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not
a <hi>ſingle,</hi> but a <hi>complex</hi> engagement; no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an <hi>abſolute,</hi> but a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional</hi>
clauſe (with many ſuch diſtinction<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is for the Kings
Perſon <hi>in the preſervation of our Religion and Liberties</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Many of you have made ſuch anſwers to them that did ſcruple the Covenant being to go to wars, or fight as occaſion ſhould be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, becauſe of that clauſe concl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing the perſon of the King.</note>: And
though the King ſhould be deſtroyed by you, you have not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
keps your Covenant, and that mens ſpirits may
be free without regret. You tell the people that the King in a
man of blood, taking hold of all whiſpering hear-ſayes and
probabilities of his wickedneſſe, to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke him odious to the
people; then the <hi>death of King</hi> James, <hi>of Prince</hi> Henery, the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:116114:36"/>
               <hi>betraying of Rochell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Love in his Sermon at Vxbridg.</note> the contriving the promoting of the Iri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
rebellion, the blood of <hi>England, Scotland, &amp; Ireland</hi> is laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
him; then the wickedneſſe, idolatry, profaneſſe, luxury,
and all kinds of impiety; of the licentious Court, looſe No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,
and lewd Gentry, are ſet forth; then God is comming
to avenge the injury and wrong, and to make inquiſition for
the blood of his people;<note place="margin">Let Mr. <hi>Love</hi> ſpeak, if there are not many old Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticlers (as they are call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) that can witneſſe this.</note> Then you pray, Lord either <hi>conv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
the King, or confound him. Lord let the prayers of thy people fall
upon his heart, or upon his head, either in ſhewres of grace upon his
ſoule, or judgements otherwayes upon him.</hi> If an Army be raiſed
up, though for its paucity and contemptibleneſſe it be called a
new Noddle, freſh-water Souldiers, &amp;c. you encourage them
notwithſtanding, calling them an Army of Saints, telling
them that God wil be with them, and wil make them his <hi>battle,
axe, and weapons of War,</hi> and that this new Noddle ſhal break in
pieces their enemies, &amp;c. When the War is ended, the Enemy
vanquiſhed, the liberties of the people recovered, the freedom
of godly, honeſt, and tender-conſcienc'd men ſecured, if that
they bring not the ſpoil of their victories, and lay them down
at your feet, and guard themſelves to ſerve you with your ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vory
meate which they have gotten (I meane ſacrificed to your
power and greatneſſe.) Nay, if they that ſit at the ſtern do no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
lay aſide all other buſineſſe (though never ſo much concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the common peace and ſafety) and doe nothing elſe but
build your Pallaces, then you run to the quiver of the holy
Scriptures, and chooſe out the ſharpeſt and keeneſt arrows
you can meet withall to wound the credite and reputation of
the Parliament and Army: and all that (having a ſuppoſed
opportunity) doe not toyle and travell to get your bread in
the ſweat of their brows, and build your houſes, though in
the blood of the whole Kingdome, then you cry out, why <hi>do
you dwell in ſeiled houſes, and the houſe of the Lord lye waſt? curſed
be he that doth the worke of the Lord negligently:</hi> You are to ſerve
the Lord with <hi>the firſt fruits</hi> of your victories and ſucceſſes:
and becauſe yee neglect the work of the Lord, and doe not put
the Crown upon the head of Chriſt, and the Scepter into his
hand, therefore he will powr forth contempt upon you, and
break you in pieces, and ſhatter you and your Forces, &amp;c. If
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:116114:36"/>
this chanting will not ſerve turn; then forgetting thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
which ſpeak of ſubjecting to authority, and of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
of <hi>deſpiſing Dominion, and ſpeaking evill of Dignities,</hi> &amp;c.
You fall upon down-right ralling againſt them; then they are
an apoſtatizing <hi>Parliament,</hi> a degenerating <hi>Parliament,</hi> a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi>
at whoſe doors may be laid <hi>all the errours, herefiet, and
blaſphemies of the times,</hi> an oppreſſing <hi>Parliament,</hi> &amp;c. If all
this will not doe; but your Temple-worke goes on ſlowly;
then the City is ſet on work, and the Countrey is excited, Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices
and others encouraged to offer violence upon the 2.
Houſes, forcing them to vote and unvote at pleaſure, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged
by ſome of your Tribt and Subſcribers (as ſhall be
made good if occaſion be) then if this will not yet doe, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacke</hi>
and <hi>Balaam</hi> cannot curſe <hi>Iſrael</hi> from <hi>Mount-Piſga,</hi> they
will ſtrive to doe it from <hi>Mount-Peor:</hi> and obſerving that the
Army (that <hi>quondam</hi> new Noddle, that Army of Saints, while
they were hopefully your ſervants) prove your ſuppoſed and
conjectured obſtructors, (I ſay ſuppoſed and conjectured, for
indeed they have ſaved your throats from being cut, whichis al
the injury that ever yet they have done you) now a rebellious
<hi>Army,</hi> an oppreſſing <hi>Army,</hi> an <hi>Army</hi> of <hi>Heretickes, Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes,
Seperatiſts,</hi> &amp;c. Then you think of a new courſe, and
Biſhops being hopefully aboliſhed, and no great danger that
they will any longer ſtand in your way, you venture in joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
with notorious Malignants, as preſuming, that though the
<hi>King</hi> and his party ſhould raiſe themſelves in the ruines of the
Army, yet Epiſcopacy is damned that could not hinder you;
then City and Countrey Petitions are promoted for a Perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
Treaty for the reſtauration of the <hi>King,</hi> in <hi>ſafety, freedome,
and honour.</hi> Then you temper your Sermons, and turne your
tongues, your lines, your language for the Royall intereſt: but
to be briefe, when nothing ſerves, but the Army prevailes, the
<hi>King</hi> is brought to condign puniſhment, a Prelaticall Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery
ſhall not be ſuffered; what patheticke crie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and moanes,
ſighs and groanes are heard in your Pulpits, wringing your
hands in bitter complaints, that the Land is ſtain'd with the
blood of our Prince, &amp;c. when alaſſe the Royall party, and
moſt judicious men with them, cannot believe but that the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:116114:37"/>
root of all this bitterneſſe is, that your crown of Cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>icall Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction
is fallen to the ground.</p>
            <p>I have a few queries to tender to your ſerious conſideration
for a finall concluſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Whether it would not be a moſt acceptable ſervice to God
and man, that you above all others, whoſe Function, Profeſſion, and
daily employment ſhould he the promotion of righteouſneſſe and juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice,
truth and peace in the world, ſhould improve your heads &amp; y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
hearts, your intereſts and opportunities, your time and your ſtudier
to compoſe our differences, make up our breaches, heale our diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
and to promote love and good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orkes amongſt all people: and
whether you thinke in your conſcience<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, you as well as others have
not beene remiſſe and negligent in your duty herein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Second<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> Whereas you complaine that the bedge of Magiſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
is broken downe, and lawfull Authority ſwallowed up in a confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
Auarchy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whether you conceive in your conſciences, that
the way to reduce all, &amp; to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cover in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſe, be to trample down
all that viſible Authority which is yet extant; You ſay we have<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e
King, no Lords, no Parliament no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> government: If ſo, is it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
farae better to thinke upon, contrive, and ſtudy to ſettle ſome go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
then that wee ſhould live together without government
(any government being better then none) it's ſaid we have had
(for a great while) a King and no King, a Parliament &amp; no Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
one party ſetting it ſelfe againſt another party, and as p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
and opportunity did appear, each party plucking the other out by
the eares, voting and unvoting, doing and undoing, no man know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
where to fixe, ſince then the foundations of government being
ſhaken, and the pillars thereof removed, and the nerves and ſinewes
broken in pieces? Is it not beſt for every party and ſociety of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en to
improve themſelves and all their intereſt in the timous ſev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lement of
ſome government amongſt us, and whether your preſent actings
have ſuch a tendency.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Whereas you complain of the contempt of the Miniſtery,
whether this bulruſh of contempt hath not growne from the mire of
contention between godly men, and whether the ſeeds thereof have
not beene ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne even from the Pulpits themſelves. You complaine
that the Armie, your diſſenting brethren and others, doe deſpiſe
and contemn the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt: but how can you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:116114:37"/>
it otherwayes, while ſuch reproach and contempt is caſt upon
them from the Miniſters, whether you can in reaſon expect it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
untill ſuch time as a more ſoft and quiet ſpirit remain in you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Whether it can in reaſon be imagined that the
Parliament and Army can be gained over unto you by theſe wayes of
bitter invectives againſt them: and if not, whether that your hope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
otherwayes can be founded upon any thing but an expectation of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
warre, and <hi>conſideratis conſider and is,</hi> what is the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of <hi>England</hi> like to be in ſuch a caſe; for God and your Countreyes
ſake if you love the one or the other conſider of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Whether that the ingenuity of the Armie, eſpecially
the Officers thereof, whoſe principles of religion and wiſdome doe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
them to beare reproaches, be not a ſnare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto you, to abuſe
them as you doe: and whether you are perſwaded in your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
the Kings Army would have ſuffered you to have given them
the like meaſure?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Whether that an over-weening opinion in you of your
popularity and publique intereſt of the Kingdoms nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſity of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,
of the clamor of the people in caſe you ſhould be called to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion
for your irregular preceedings, together with a ſecret kinde of
pride and ambition of ſome ſmall ſufferings, to contract, if posſible,
the credite, glory, and repute of Martyrs or ſufferings for Chriſt, be
not likewiſe another ſnare of death unto you in this kind? and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
this be ſutable to that ingenuity and candor which becomes the
Miniſters of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Whether that the ſpirit of perverſneſſe doth not blaſt
your abilities to the popular obſervation of your apprehenſive Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,
cauſing you to ſpend your precious hours in Studies and pulpits,
in the ſapleſſe ſavour of ſimple notions. I ſhall only inſtance in one of
your Rabbies, Mr. <hi>E. C.</hi> of <hi>A. B.</hi> We ſhould pray ſaith he to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
from 6. (<hi>ſhallow</hi>) deeps, the deep of Anarchy (<hi>or a boundle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s
Presbytery</hi>) the deep of perjury (<hi>chiefly that of the Clergy</hi>) the
deep of tolleration (<hi>eſpecially of the State-troubling faction</hi>) the
deep of an everlaſting Army (<hi>or the disbanding our preſent Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi>)
the deep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of ſhedding the blood of our King<note n="*" place="margin">That hath made no more conſcience of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lling men then Moles, and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ople then piſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mires, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> burning their houſes then walps neſts.</note>, (or ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring the
great murtherer of the Kingdome) the deep of Hell (or that dungeon
thereof, pav'd with the creaſts of that ſcandalous Clergy) let m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of
reaſon judge of the profundity of this Divinity, whether this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o
preach Chriſt crucified, or to crucifie Chriſt preached, may quickely
be determined.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
